<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eshcol, or Grapes (among) thorns. As they were delivered in a Thanksgiving sermon, to the Honourable House of Commons. By John Bond, Mr. of the Savoy.</title>
            <author>Bond, John, 1612-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E452_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864323</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77002)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E452[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eshcol, or Grapes (among) thorns. As they were delivered in a Thanksgiving sermon, to the Honourable House of Commons. By John Bond, Mr. of the Savoy.</title>
                  <author>Bond, John, 1612-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. for Samuell Gellibrand, at the Brazen Serpent in St. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A thanksgiving sermon before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "13 July 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <!--The intrusive material in this book and image set (images 5b - 7a) appears to represent the conclusion of the Thomason copy of: The Moderate Intelligencer, no. 173 (July 6 to July 13 1648) EEBO ID 53403917_161970 VID 161970 Thomason 72:E.452[28] which otherwise lacks its conclusion. http://gateway.proquest.com / openurl?ctx<SEG REND="decorInit">v</SEG>er=Z39.88-2003&res<SEG REND="decorInit">i</SEG>d=xri:eebo&rft<SEG REND="decorInit">i</SEG>d=xri:eebo:citation:53403917-->
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116550:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ESHCOL, OR Grapes (among) Thorns.</p>
                  <p>As they were delivered IN A Thankſgiving Sermon, to the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
                  <p>BY JOHN BOND, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> of the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 76. ver. 10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Surely the wrath of man ſhall praiſe thee: the remainder of wrath ſhalt thou reſtraine.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Nam de eo quid dicam, qui in murmure &amp; impatientiâ obſtinato per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durat animo, aut quem poenitet adhaeſiſſe deo, &amp; contra mortem, &amp; contra rationem, bonum factum poenitentiâ comitatur, qui ſine dubio miſerationibus Dei non modò non habet gratiam, ſed contumeliam reddit? &amp;c.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Bern. de Sept. miſericord: Serm. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Quicunque Gratos eſſe docet, &amp; hominum cauſſam agit, &amp; deorum.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Senec. 2. de Benef. c. 30.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Samuell Gellibrand,</hi> at the Brazen Serpent in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> CHURCH-Yard. 1648.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116550:2"/>
                  <head>TO The Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, Now Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable Senate;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe at laſt preſent you with that <hi>Cluſter of Grapes,</hi> which have beene longer in the <hi>Preſſe</hi> then your Order doth ſeeme to permit: they are called the <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 13. &amp; 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Grapes of Eſchol,</hi> becauſe that Cluſter was both a taſt, and pledge of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to the few <hi>beleeving ſpies;</hi> but to the
<pb facs="tcp:116550:3"/>reſt, and to all other murmurers, they proved <hi>Grapes of gall, and bitter Cluſters,</hi> as <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 32. v. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith afterward. That <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Eſchol</hi> would be <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly read</hi> by us all, in this juncture of <hi>time,</hi> for we may there fully find our <hi>preſent</hi> conditions and diviſions, and gueſſe at our <hi>future</hi> eſtate. If you would bee in the ſame ſide and caſe with <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> I have two leſſons to commend unto you. 1. Yee muſt be <hi>men of</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Num. 13. v. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>another ſpirit, and muſt follow the Lord fully:</hi> an hard taske at ſuch a time; but you may be excellently directed in it by that <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Burroughs</hi> Gracious ſpirit, <hi>ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> holy man now with God. 2. You had need to <hi>plead</hi> ſtrongly with all murmurers, both for God, and for their advance into the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reſt, yea, though they <hi>bid</hi> 
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Numb. 14. v. 10. v. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtone</hi> you <hi>with ſtones;</hi> leſt the <hi>Lord ſmite us all with peſtilence, and diſinherite us.</hi> For mine owne part, I know that there are not onely a ſort of fierce <hi>enemies,</hi> which like the Turkiſh <hi>Ianizaries</hi> will bee ready to ſtave, and breake the cask, becauſe they are not to ſhare in this wine; and to theſe I ſay, as he in the Epigram—<hi>Rode caper vites</hi>—; But there are alſo many voluntary <note n="f" place="margin">Jerem. 35.</note> 
                     <hi>Rechabites</hi> amongſt our <hi>friends,</hi> which will not touch with theſe <hi>cluſters,</hi> becauſe they like not (perhaps) the <hi>vine</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:116550:3"/>on which they grow. Alas! is there no way yet to make us all of a <hi>diet</hi> at our <hi>neceſſary</hi> food? Surely, <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>thirſt</hi> will bring us to it. In our Hiſtory of <hi>Eſhcol,</hi> I find two grand <hi>cauſes</hi> of that murmuring.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Baſe carnall <hi>feare</hi> of the enemies ſtrength. <note n="b" place="margin">Num. 13. v. 27, 28.</note> 
                     <hi>Surely the land floweth with milke and hony, and this is the fruit of it, nevertheleſſe the people be ſtrong that dwell in the land, &amp;c.</hi> The work is like to be long and bloudy. But what, ſhall we on that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <note n="c" place="margin">Numb. 14. v. 1, 2, 3, 4. v. 9</note> 1. <hi>Repent of our coming out of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>and make us Captaines to returne thither againe?</hi> Or, 2. Shall we beleeve <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> that ſay; <hi>Feare them not, for they are bread for us?</hi> And will any man diſlike a <hi>loafe</hi> of bread for its <hi>bigneſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Cauſe was <hi>jealouſie</hi> againſt, <hi>non-confiding</hi> in, the <hi>Cluſter-bearers.</hi> The Lord remove all ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blockes, and heart-diviſions, now that we are upon the <hi>borders</hi> of <hi>Eſhcol,</hi> or of <hi>Hormah.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Num. 14. v. 45.</note> They are Satans laſt <hi>make</hi> againſt us, hee could not beate us by a <hi>common</hi> enemy, and therfore would now break us by <hi>one another;</hi> as that <hi>Iuno</hi> in the <note n="d" place="margin">Sen: Her. Fur. Quaeris Alcidae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem? nemo eſt niſi ipſe.</note> Tragedy, dealt with <hi>Hercules</hi> when hee had conquered <hi>Hell,</hi> and was returned ſafe from all his <hi>labours.</hi> She concludes, <hi>none can conquer Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,
<pb facs="tcp:116550:4"/>but Alcides.</hi> None can conquer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering party but <hi>themſelves.</hi> No <hi>Arrow</hi> can wound us unleſſe it bee made with our own <hi>feathers.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Melancttho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis dictum.</note> There are now but theſe foure <hi>choyſes</hi> left to us; either to <hi>continue</hi> ſtill in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> or to <hi>returne</hi> back again to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> or to <hi>truſt</hi> God and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo <hi>enter</hi> into that good reſt. And tis notable, that theſe very Iſraelites which <hi>firſt murmured</hi> and recoiled becauſe of <hi>difficulties,</hi> they could, would, did endeavour and adventure upon the worke <hi>at laſt,</hi> when their unbeliefe and murmuring had <hi>ſhut the dore,</hi> but then it was too late; then <hi>Eſhcol</hi> was turned to <note n="a" place="margin">Cap. 14. v. 41, 42, 43.</note> 
                     <hi>Hormah,</hi> even diſcomfiture and deſolation. Surely, there are common <hi>enemies</hi> and dangers <hi>enough,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 13.9.</note> there is work and wages <hi>enough</hi> in earth, or heaven, to imploy us all, wee need not to <note n="b" place="margin">Mic. 7. v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>hunt</hi> one another <hi>with a net.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I <hi>forget</hi> that I am writing an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and that to a <hi>Parliament.</hi> Pardon I beſeech you my neceſſary <hi>zeale</hi> at ſuch a time, ſome men (they ſay) reade nothing of Sermons but the <hi>Epiſtles;</hi> and I would faine be ſome kind of (poore) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:116550:4"/>
                     <hi>Ligature</hi> to this broken bone. Now the mighty God, the wonderfull Counſeller, the Prince of peace, ſtrengthen, direct you, to <hi>Land</hi> the great <hi>intereſts</hi> of our Religion, and Rights, without wracke or waſte. So prayeth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Savoy,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>The unworthieſt of Your Servants, JOHN BOND.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116550:5"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Iovis</hi> 20. Julii, 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Rdered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, That Maſter <hi>Hill</hi> doe give thanks to Maſter <hi>Bond,</hi> that preached before the Houſe of Commons at the Thankſgiving yeſterday, and that his Sermon bee forthwith printed and publiſhed, and that he have the like priviledge in printing his Sermon, as others in the like kinde uſually have had.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen: Elſynge Cler: Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="license">
                  <p>I appoint <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>IOHN BOND.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116550:7"/>
                  <head>A THANKSGIVING SERMON before the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 50.23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Whoſo offereth praiſe, glorifieth me; and to him that ordereth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>worke</hi> of the Lord in theſe <hi>times,</hi> and his word in this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> do appeare unto me <hi>much alike:</hi> in our <hi>firſt warre</hi> the Lord made it his worke to <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 30. v. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>ſift</hi> theſe three Nations ſomewhat generally, and as it were, with a <hi>wider</hi> and courſer <hi>ſieve:</hi> ſo wide and courſe it was, that much <hi>chaffe and ſtraw</hi> went through it with the <hi>wheat,</hi> and onely the groſſer traſh, as ſtickes and ſtones, did ſtay behinde. I meane (generally) the open profane and <hi>ſcandalous party</hi> in theſe Lands. And there was a ſpeciall providence in that, for ſhould the <hi>firſt ſieve</hi> have been too ſhy and <hi>fine,</hi> it might have kept back ſo great a maſſe and <hi>weight</hi> on that ſide, as might have borne and <hi>broken out</hi> the <hi>bottome</hi> or floore of the ſieve. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord did then ſort and ſift us as the <hi>worke</hi> would <hi>beare</hi> at that <hi>time.</hi> But now, behold in this <hi>ſecond warre,</hi> he is ſifting the ſifted againe with a much ſiner rince: The <hi>profane party</hi> was then ſand out; but now he is ſeparating between the <hi>faithfull</hi> and the <hi>formaliſt.</hi> Like that <hi>worke,</hi> runneth this <hi>Pſalme:</hi> for it <note n="b" place="margin">Analyſis of the Pſalm.</note> containeth the great <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> or <hi>Arraignment</hi> of the <hi>hypocrite.</hi> In which,</p>
                  <p n="1">I. We read the convention of the <hi>Court,</hi> 
                     <note n="x" place="margin">The Seſſion.</note> and ſitting downe of the <hi>Bench:</hi> the <hi>witneſſes</hi> are the <hi>whole earth,</hi> which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">v. 1.</note> from the <hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
                     <hi>riſing of the Sunne</hi> to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116550:8"/>
                     <hi>going downe thereof.</hi> The <hi>place</hi> is out of <note n="d" place="margin">v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>perfection of beauty.</hi> The <hi>guard</hi> and executioners, <note n="e" place="margin">v. 3.</note> a <hi>fire ſhall devoure before him,</hi> and it ſhall be very <hi>Tempeſtuous round about him.</hi> The <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">v. 4.</note> heaven and earth. The <note n="g" place="margin">v. 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Judge, El, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovah, Elohim;</hi> if you will, the whole Trinity: The Lord is Judge himſelfe. And the ſummoned <hi>delinquents</hi> or malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, in generall, <hi>viſible</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">v. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Saints</hi> and facrificing <hi>Covenanters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2 The proceſſe</note> II. The <hi>Proceſſe,</hi> or proceedings upon them: And theſe are of <hi>two</hi> ſorts, according to the <hi>number</hi> and kindes of the <hi>arraigned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sort of the Arraigned are called the Lords owne <note n="a" place="margin">v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he their God: And that as ſome conceive, in the <hi>ſtricteſt ſenſe,</hi> they were <note n="b" place="margin">Etſi in ratione cultus errarunt, animo tamea erant ad colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Deum verè ac ſincerè dedito &amp;c. Muſculus ad loc.</note> 
                     <hi>ſincere hearts</hi> though too carnall in leaning too much upon bodily exerciſes and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward duties of religion, upon ſacrifices and burnt offerings, in <note n="c" place="margin">v. 8, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Bullockes</hi> and <hi>Hee Goats.</hi> To theſe he hath two words.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>A reproofe</hi> of their meere carnall, at leaſt <hi>too</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">v. 8.9.</note> 
                     <hi>carnall</hi> and extrinſecall <hi>ſervices</hi> or forme of godlineſſe, in which they did reſt and bleſſe themſelves too much, neglecting (meane while) the <hi>inſide</hi> and power thereof. And the <hi>reaſon</hi> is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is not as a man or a beaſt, as a Bell and a Dragon, that <note n="e" place="margin">v. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>needeth</hi> to be fed with carnall oblations, with meate and drinke: Nay, if he had need or deſire to ſuch brutiſh ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, he hath <hi>enough</hi> of his owne, he has them all in his hand and power, he needeth not to beg or borrow from them, <note n="f" place="margin">v. 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
                     <hi>All beaſts and cattell, all fowle and wild beaſts,</hi> they are his, or with him. And therefore,</p>
                  <p n="2">2 He doth exhort them to <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Compoſitum jus, faſque ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, ſanctos que receſſus Mentis, &amp; incoctum generoſo pectus honeſto. Perſ. Sat.</hi> 2.</note> reall, ſpirituall, inward ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. Of which ſort <hi>three</hi> ſpeciall ones are named, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The oblation of praiſe. 2. The payment of vowes. 3. The prayer of faith. All theſe are ſuch <hi>hard</hi> and ſolid <hi>ground</hi> that if you try a <hi>founderd formaliſt</hi> upon them, and put him to it, you ſhall ſoone finde him halting, though he ſeemed to runne nimbly in ſome ſofter and eaſier duties.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <note n="h" place="margin">v. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Offer to God thanksgiving;</hi> this is no worke for hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites: no, <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 64. v. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>The righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, and ſhall truſt in him, and all the upright in heart ſhall glory.</hi> But the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116550:8"/>heart is as an <hi>Aſſe</hi> to this <hi>Harp.</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Iob. 27. v. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Will he delight him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the Almighty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>And pay thy vowes to the moſt High.</hi> The hypocrite is as forward in promiſing as any, yea commonly more large than the reall Saint, becauſe he doth purpoſe to give <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Verba dare.</hi>
                     </note> no thing but promiſes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <note n="m" place="margin">v. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble.</hi> Herein alſo the <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite</hi> will <hi>quickly tire,</hi> if he doth beginne it at all; <note n="n" place="margin">Iob 27. v. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Will he alwayes call upon God?</hi> King <hi>Iehoram wore ſackcloth</hi> for a while, when <hi>Samaria</hi> was diſtreſt, <note n="o" place="margin">2 Kings 6. v. 30, 31.33.</note> but <hi>how ſoone</hi> growes he impatient and rayleth? <hi>This evill is of the Lord, why ſhould I waite for the Lord any longer?</hi> Theſe are the Lords proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the better party of theſe <hi>Indicted</hi> ones.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sort are called the <note n="a" place="margin">v. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers omnis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris dei &amp; verae pietatis &amp;c. Mollen.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>wicked,</hi> 1. inwardly; And yet a kinde of <hi>profeſſors</hi> too, for they doe <hi>declare his ſtatutes</hi> and take his <hi>Covenant into their mouthes,</hi> though in reall practice they are wide enough, for they are <note n="b" place="margin">v. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>haters</hi> of <hi>inſtruction</hi> and they <hi>caſt his words behinde them.</hi> Thus they were rotten at the <hi>core,</hi> and therefore it is not long before it comes out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Skinne,</hi> yea they proceed to breake the <hi>ſecond Table,</hi> though not in the moſt <hi>groſſe degree</hi> and manner; they <note n="c" place="margin">v. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> with the <hi>thiefe,</hi> they are concealours and acceſſories, though not principals; they partake with adulterers; that is, ſecretly under hand they ſtick not to act ſuch abominable wickedneſſes, or at leaſt ſome way to ſhare in the profits and commutations. In ſhort, they <note n="d" place="margin">v. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>give their mouthes to evill,</hi> and <hi>frame deceit with their tongues,</hi> Yea, finally they <note n="e" place="margin">v. 20.</note> fit in the <hi>ſeat of the ſcorner,</hi> and doe <hi>ſlander</hi> their owne <hi>brethren</hi> and neereſt kinſmen. And that which doth <hi>incourage:</hi> them in all this, is the Lords ſilence, and patience, <hi>becauſe</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. v. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>ſentence againſt their evill works is not ſpeedly executed, therefore</hi> they are ready to juſtifie themſelves, and condemne the Lord. But, ſaith he, <note n="g" place="margin">v. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>I will reprove thee, and ſet them in order before thine eyes,</hi> I will bring them forth, and marſhall them againſt thee in <hi>battell array.</hi> And hence</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">3 The ſentence.</note> III. The <hi>verdict</hi> and <hi>ſentence</hi> upon the whole matter, which according to the <hi>two parties</hi> is alſo <hi>twofold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116550:9"/>
                  <p n="1">1. A cenſure of <hi>terrour</hi> to the laſt and <hi>worſt ſort</hi> of delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, in caſe they continue in their impenitency: <note n="h" place="margin">v. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Now conſider this yee that forget God, leſt I teare you in peeces, and there be none to deliver you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Explication of the words.</note> 2. A cordiall and <hi>promiſe</hi> to the former and <hi>better ſort</hi> of the arraigned, if they returne to reall duty, and a well ordered way. <note n="i" place="margin">v. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſo offereth praiſe glorifieth me,</hi> and to him that order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</p>
                  <p>There is not much to doe about the <hi>reading</hi> of the words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Who ſo offereth praiſe]</hi> Or, he that ſacrificeth confeſſion. There is a <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Confeſſio ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina eſt, aut Beccati, aut laudis. Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 29.</note> twofold confeſſion; of ſinne, and of praiſe; ſo above, <note n="b" place="margin">v. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Sacrifice or offer unto God a confeſſion.</hi> And by <hi>[praiſe]</hi> in the text, we are to underſtand the <hi>whole inward</hi> worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Glorifieth, or honoreth mee]</hi> The <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Greeke</hi> thus, the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praiſe, in the <hi>abſtract,</hi> ſhall glorifie me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[And to him that ordereth his converſation aright]</hi> In the Originall, that <hi>putteth, compoſeth, diſpoſeth</hi> the <hi>way:</hi> for that word Way is left in its full latitude in the originall. But others read this in a farre <hi>different ſenſe,</hi> thus, <hi>And there is the way in which I will ſhew the ſalvation of God.</hi> Thus the Papiſts generally, from their <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Et illic iter quo oſtendam, vel ibi eſt via in quaoſtendam.</hi>
                     </note> Vulgar, and out of the <note n="e" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint. Their difference and miſtake (I conceive) did ariſe from the likeneſſe of two Monoſyllables in the originall; <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ibi, illic.</hi>
                     </note> One of which being an Adverb doth ſignifie, <hi>here, there,</hi> or <hi>thence.</hi> The <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>poſuit, appoſuit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuit.</hi>
                     </note> other, a defective verbe ſignifies, to put, order, compoſe, as before. But we follow the fountaine, and reade it as in our laſt tranſlation, <hi>To him that ordereth the way &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[I will ſhew]</hi> Or, I will <hi>make,</hi> or <hi>cauſe</hi> him to <hi>ſee.</hi> And that not flatly or <hi>barely,</hi> but with affection and <hi>delight:</hi> as elſewhere, <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 112. v. 8. <hi>Quaſt iucundo frui ſpectaculo.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>His heart is eſtabliſhed, he ſhall not be afraid, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he ſee his deſire upon his enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[The ſalvation of God]</hi> By it underſtand we, either extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>great</hi> and divine ſalvation, as, <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 104. v. 16.</note> The <hi>Trees of God,</hi> and the <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 34. v. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Mountaines of God,</hi> that is, faire and eminent ones: Or, that God will aſſure and make good this ſalvation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116550:9"/>all ſuch: Or, he ſpeakes in the third perſon that the <hi>emphaſis</hi> may be the greater.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Diviſion of the words.</note> The text, if we looke upon it without dependence, doth containe the <hi>whole twofold</hi> end and <hi>duty of man;</hi> with the proper and ſpeciall <hi>meanes to each</hi> of thoſe ends, and theſe cannot well be divided.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Principall and Ultimate end of man, in reſpect <hi>of God,</hi> is to <hi>glorifie him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>meanes</hi> to that end, is all <hi>duty,</hi> but eſpecially that of <hi>praiſe</hi> and thankſgiving; <hi>Who ſo offereth praiſe glorifieth me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The next principall end of man, in reſpect of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> which is alſo ſubordinate to that former end, is to be ſaved, or to <hi>ſee the ſalvation of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And an eſpeciall <hi>meanes</hi> unto this end, is the <hi>right order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the way.</hi> Thus the words doe containe <hi>[the praiſe of Thanksgiving.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who ſo offereth praiſe, glorifieth me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is true of every <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>right ſervice</hi> that is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by any ſonne or ſervant of God. <note n="a" place="margin">Malach. 1. v. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>A ſonne honoureth his father, and a ſervant his maſter.</hi> But it muſt needs be <hi>eminently</hi> true of the ſervice of <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> which alone is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly named in the words, and called a <hi>glorifying</hi> or <hi>honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Hence <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Thanksgiving to God, is a very glorious and tranſcendent ſervice.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a <hi>threefold Crowne</hi> or Emphaſis put upon the head of this ſervice in this <hi>Pſalme</hi> and <hi>Text.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is put (in this <hi>Pſalme</hi>) in the <hi>front</hi> of thoſe <hi>three</hi> Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall trying <hi>duties</hi> which are ſet up as the ſtandard to weigh all profeſſors by them; namely, Praiſe, Payment of vowes, and Prayer. And the firſt of theſe you ſee is Praiſe, <note n="b" place="margin">v. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Offer to God thanksgiving:</hi> therefore it is a duty of the firſt and <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forme;</hi> ſuch a <hi>Key</hi> as no hypocrite can ſo counterfeit, but that he will eaſily be eſpyed; though he hath the fiddle (as he ſaid) yet he wants the ſtick: And therefore that <hi>[Lord I thank thee]</hi> of the <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 18. v. 11.</note> Phariſee, is not a praiſing <hi>of God</hi> ſo much as of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116550:10"/>
                     <hi>ſelfe,</hi> not a thankſgiving but an <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Saturatus ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabat. Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 49.</note> 
                     <hi>eaſing</hi> of himſelfe, ſaith one: yea every one that readeth him ſpiritually, findeth him trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at the threſhold.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Againe in the <hi>text,</hi> praiſing is put as I ſaid, for all <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and ſpirituall worſhip, and is oppoſed to all thoſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſacrifices and burnt offerings before mentioned, as if it were the <hi>touchſtone</hi> of all <hi>inward ſacrifices</hi>; [<hi>Who ſo offereth praiſe;</hi>] as if he had ſaid, every one that doth and can <hi>praiſe</hi> me aright, <note n="a" place="margin">Pſalme 69. v. 30, 31.</note> he can doubtleſſe performe all other <hi>parts</hi> of worſhip as he ought. Yea this is the <hi>ſurpaſſing</hi> ſervice; <hi>I will praiſe the name of God with a ſong, this alſo ſhall pleaſe the Lord better then a Bullock that hath hornes and hoofes,</hi> better then a calfe that is overgrowne, or of a <note n="b" place="margin">Mich. 6. v. 6.</note> yeare old.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Chryſoſt. ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> This duty eſpecially is here ſaid to <hi>glorifie</hi> or <hi>honour God:</hi> this is an high and hyperbolicall expreſſion indeed, for honour wee ſay, is in the <note n="d" place="margin">Honor eſt in honorante non in honorato.</note> 
                     <hi>honorer</hi> not in the honored; and what? can the poore worme man give or add any thing unto God? it is elſewhere called a <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 103 1.</note> 
                     <hi>bleſſing</hi> of God, <hi>Bleſſe the Name of the Lord, O my ſoule:</hi> Now ſaith the Spirit to the Hebrewes, <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 7. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>The leſſer is bleſſed of the greater.</hi> Nay once more, it is called in the Word a <hi>magnifying,</hi> that is, a <hi>greatning</hi> of God; an <hi>exalting,</hi> that is, an <hi>heightning</hi> of his name: <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 34. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>O mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his name together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Demonſtra∣tions. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how can theſe things bee? <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Lord takes it as</hi> an honour, and <hi>men</hi> looke upon it as <hi>a giving</hi> of honour to God when wee doe ſo <hi>record,</hi> declare, <hi>proclaime,</hi> the greatneſſe and goodneſſe of the Lord, whether of his being, or workes, that others do <hi>ſee more</hi> of him and in him then ever they did perceive or believe before; <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 26. v. 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Sing praiſe to the Lord which dwelleth in Sion, declare amongſt the people his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. That I may publiſh with a voyce of thanksgiving, and tell of all thy wondrous wooks.</hi> But for methods ſake, which is the mother of memory, the ſpeciall <hi>excellency</hi> and tranſcendency of <hi>this ſervice,</hi> may be demonſtrated in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. From the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſiveneſſe and perfection of this duty.</note> 1. They appeare by its <hi>comprehenſiveneſſe and perfections.</hi> It is the <hi>Sea,</hi> that is, both the fountaine, and receptacle of all other duties. The Preacher ſaith of the ſea, <note n="i" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>all the rivers run
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116550:10"/>into it, yet the ſen is not full, unto the place whence the rivers come thither they returne againe:</hi> that is, all rivers runne into the ſea, and (as ſome ſay) from the ſea they ariſe againe. Though this bee quarreld in Philoſophy, yet I am ſure it is true in Divinity, concerning the <hi>ocean</hi> of <hi>thanksgiving.</hi> Let us lay our inſtance in the continuall duty of <hi>prayer,</hi> which (as one ſaith) is the <hi>bread and ſalt</hi> at every ſpirituall meale; for it muſt be <hi>one</hi> whatſoever is the <hi>other.</hi> Behold, <hi>thanksgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is both the roote and fruit, the beginning, middle, and end; yea the both ends of this ſervice. The <hi>beginning,</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Coloſ. 1. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>We give thanks to God and the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes for you:</hi> there it is to prayer as the <hi>needle</hi> to the <hi>thred.</hi> The <hi>middle,</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Coloſ. 4. v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Continue in prayer, and watch in the ſame with thanksgiving:</hi> there are the three <hi>conditions</hi> of prayer, Perſeverance, Watchfulneſſe and Gratitude. And unto this laſt ( <note n="c" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Davenant. ad loc.</hi>
                     </note> ſaith one) we are <hi>alwayes</hi> bound, whether wee looke to Gods gifts, promiſes, delayes, or denials; there is cauſe of thankſgiving for every one of theſe, and he is mercifull in them all towards his Saints. The like place is, <note n="d" place="margin">Philip. 4. v. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Bee carefull in nothing, but in every thing, by prayer and ſupplication, with thanksgiving let your requeſts be made knowne unto God:</hi> there it is as the <hi>Axle-tree</hi> upon which the duty of prayer doth turn it ſelfe. Yea, ſee it at <hi>both ends</hi> of prayer, <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 105.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>O give thankes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, call upon his name, make knowne his deeds among the people; ſing unto him &amp;c.</hi> Nay we are commanded this duty in all caſes. <note n="f" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. v. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>In every thing give thanks, for this is the will of God in Chriſt Ieſus concerning you:</hi> In every condition, ſay ſome; but I thinke it cloſer Divinity and Expoſition, to ſay, and with every duty, for praiſe is the beſt ſawce to God and man in every Goſpell ſacrifice: and therefore is put for the <hi>whole.</hi> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 13.15.</note> 
                     <hi>By him therefore let us offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips, giving thanks unto his name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. From its Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note> 2. This ſervice is glorious and tranſcendent in reſpect of its <hi>actors and ſubject;</hi> It is not every one that is fit to learne Muſique; neither the witleſſe, nor the wicked foole can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme or counterfeit this duty artificially. There is not any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116550:11"/>other outward <hi>ſervice</hi> of religion (that I remember) which I cannot ſhew you ſome profane ones or groſſe hypocrites have been <hi>acting</hi> it handſomely in Scripture, whereas I never finde them (and I think I am right) medling with this; King <hi>Saul</hi> was at his ſacrificing, though unſeaſonably; at his Altar building, and enquiring of the Lord; and all this to get victory and ſucceſſes, ſome of which he did obtain, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 11. v. 11.</note> Ammonites, againſt the <note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 14. v. 20.</note> Philiſtines, againſt the <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 15. v. 7.</note> Amalekites. But doe yee ever read a word of his <hi>Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings?</hi> King <hi>Ahab</hi> did beleeve the Prophet and <note n="d" place="margin">1 Kin. 21. v. 27.</note> humbled himſelfe, and was rewarded according to his worke; but <hi>what thanks</hi> did he ever return? No, no, the formaliſt that can go (as I ſaid) ſoundly and roundly in the ſmoother and ſofter ground of other duties, becauſe they may have more of ſelfe in them, yet turn him upon this grand ſervice of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and he will halt. Saith the Holy Ghoſt, <note n="e" place="margin">Iob 27. v. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Can he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light himſelfe in the Lord?</hi> It is almoſt an <hi>uncounterfeitable</hi> ſervice. And hence it is that the Saints of the <hi>higheſt forme</hi> are called upon for this performance. <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 22. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye that feare the Lord, praiſe him.</hi> And, <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 113. v. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye ſervants of the Lord, praiſe ye the name of the Lord.</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 33. v. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Praiſe is comely for the upright.</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 149. v. 1.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord, ſing unto the Lord a new ſong, and his praiſe inthe congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Saints. Let the ſaints be ioyfull in glory.</hi> No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail then if now adaies the profane beaſts amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, doe ſcoffingly bid the ſaints and holy ones, to keep their <hi>Thanksgiving Daies.</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 14. v. 18, 19, 20.</note> It is a ſervice for a Melchiſedeck, a <hi>King of Peace, and a Prieſt of the moſt high God,</hi> for an <hi>Abraham,</hi> the father of the faithfull; for a <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Miriam,</hi> for a <hi>Deborah, Baruck,</hi> &amp;c. The truth is that the holieſt and higheſt Saints on earth, are too low, they are <hi>bunglers</hi> for this duty, whilſt here beneath; and their choiceſt ſongs are but a <hi>tuning</hi> of the inſtrument, towards perfect praiſes. The heaven of heavens is the proper Quire, and the Choriſters are <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 12. v. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable companies of Angels, and the ſouls of iuſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:</hi> It is to be their everlaſting work and wages to ſing <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujahs</hi> before the Throne, and unto the Lambe. See them at it, in their glory. <note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 7 v. 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Amen, Bleſſing, and glory, and wiſdome,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116550:11"/>and thanksgiving, and honour, and power, and might, be unto our God for ever and ever, Amen.</hi> Thus <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> is the onely Celeſtiall, Angelicall, eternall ſervice and Ordinance. So as what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of <hi>Charity</hi> amongſt, yea beyond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces, that may I apply unto <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> beyond, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, all other religious duties, <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 13. v. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Thanksgiving never faileth, but whether there bee</hi> prayers, <hi>they ſhall faile, whether there bee</hi> preachings, <hi>they ſhall ceaſe, whether there bee</hi> Sacraments, <hi>they ſhall vaniſh away;</hi> thankſgiving, like <hi>Moſes</hi> his rod, ſhall devoure, and eat up all other Ordinances, and therefore the greateſt of all is thankſgiving.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Becauſe of its ſpeciall ends and effects.</note> 3. This ſervice is ſo <hi>glorious,</hi> in reſpect of its ſpeciall <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>effects.</hi> It is a moſt <hi>unbottoming,</hi> unſelfing, humbling, melting, kindling duty. It <hi>ſtrikes out</hi> the <hi>bottome</hi> of fleſh and nature, carrying out all unto God. <hi>Joy</hi> (they ſay) is an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that carryeth out al the blond and ſpirits from the heart and inward parts towards the object, as it were, to meet and welcome it. Heare <hi>Iacob</hi> a little in his <hi>begging</hi> thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at Mahanaim, <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 32.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Iſaac, the Lord which ſaid unto me, Returne unto thy Country, and to thy kindred, and I will deale well with thee: I am not worthy of</hi> [or, <hi>I am leſſe then] the leaſt of all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and of all the trueth which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; for with my ſtaffe I paſſed over this Iordan, and now I am become two bands.</hi> Do you not <hi>ſeeme to ſee</hi> the good Man holding his cudgell in his hand, and humbly looking downe upon it, whileſt hee ſpeaks to this purpoſe? <q rend="margQuotes">Alas! I was not <hi>worth</hi> this <hi>ſticke</hi> in all the world when I was forced to <hi>flee</hi> for my life, on foot, alone, from my fathers houſe, and was faine to take up an hard <hi>Stone-burrough</hi> for my pillow, and the blew <hi>heavens</hi> for my Canopie, and now ſee what a little <hi>Army</hi> the Lord hath made me?</q> Oh if one could have <hi>exchanged hearts</hi> with <hi>Iacob</hi> for an <hi>houre</hi> at that time, how would his heart have warmed ones breaſt! <hi>Nothing</hi> to <hi>Iacob,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>Nothing</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> but all to <hi>Iehovah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the example and expreſſions of good <hi>old David</hi> in ſuch a like caſe, are ſo <hi>raviſhing,</hi> that you had need to looke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116550:12"/>to your hearts, and gird them up, before you turne to the place. It was when he had been caſting about to glorifie God by <hi>building</hi> him an houſe: his will is accepted for the deed, and to boot the Lord ſends a very glorious <hi>promiſe</hi> by <hi>Nathan</hi> concerning the building of <hi>Davids</hi> owne houſe. <note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 7. v. 118.</note> 
                     <hi>Then went King David in and ſate before the Lord.</hi> Good old man! was he ſo aged that he could not <hi>ſtand</hi> or <hi>kneele?</hi> Or rather, had the Lords mercifull meſſage ſo <hi>carryed out</hi> his bloud and ſpirits as to weaken his heart within? Sure I am this was not an uſuall poſture, to <hi>ſit</hi> before the Lord. But we muſt conceive him creeping and panting by the way, from his owne houſe, unto the Lords; and ſo al-to-be-melted, and halfe <hi>breathleſſe,</hi> he falleth downe into his chaire, and ſaith, <hi>Who am I, O Lord God, and what is my fathers houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto? Who am I?</hi> What, had <hi>David</hi> forgotten his own name? or did he not know himſelfe, that hee doth aske, who he is? I read of ſome that through length of <hi>time</hi> and brutiſh <hi>ſenſuality</hi> have forgotten their owne names. But ſurely nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe had befallen good <hi>David;</hi> no, he had onely loſt himſelfe and all his fathers houſe in the <hi>ſea</hi> of the Lords preſent goodneſſe: he is <hi>amazed</hi> to thinke how hee got up to that condition, <hi>That thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>whither</hi> the Lord was now farther carrying them; <note place="margin">ver. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>And this was yet a ſmall thing in thy ſight, O Lord God, but thou haſt ſpoken alſo of thy ſervants houſe for a great while to come; and is this the manner of man, O Lord God?</hi> Lord, ſaith he, I am <hi>banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt,</hi> I am broken with the <hi>former debt</hi> that I owe unto thee, I have nothing at all to pay my <hi>arrears,</hi> for old unſpeakeable favours and mercies; and wilt thou <hi>truſt me,</hi> and mine with more, greater, and <hi>future favours?</hi> Surely this is not the <hi>courſe</hi> of the <hi>world;</hi> for men doe require us to pay one ſcore when we make another. But mee thinks his next words (if we could looke thoroughly into them) are the moſt paſſionate and emphaticall of all: <note n="a" place="margin">ver. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>And what can David ſay more unto thee?</hi> Every <hi>word</hi> hath its <hi>weight,</hi> and his interrogation and appeale, have their eſpeciall weight; But the <hi>principall</hi> thing to be noted is, that he doth <hi>name</hi> his <hi>owne name</hi> unto God,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116550:12"/>which is an unuſuall and ſurpaſſing ſtraine of <hi>rhetorick,</hi> though ſometimes taken up in the moſt melting petitions, and <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 14. v. 23.</note> earneſt expoſtulations.</p>
                  <p>The ſame ſelf-emptying effect of this grace of <hi>thanfulneſſe</hi> is to be found in other Pſalmiſts, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 5. v. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Not unto us, ô Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give the glory.</hi> He doth empty himſelf wholly, and as it were <hi>ſhakes</hi> the bag by the bottom after all was out; he thruſteth away ſelf-glorying with <hi>both hands,</hi> that he might be ſure that nothing of the creature ſhould be left behind. And in the next Pſalm, that thankfull Saint doth <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 116. v. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>catechize</hi> his own heart, and <hi>caſteth up</hi> his eſtate to ſee if there were any thing in it worth the giving unto God, <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 116. v. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits towards me?</hi> He doth turn the <hi>diſh</hi> (as we ſay) for a <hi>bit</hi> worth the preſenting, and at laſt not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing that he can think good enough, he doth give the whole unto the Lord. <note n="e" place="margin">v. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>O Lord, truly I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant,</hi> without a complement, <hi>and the ſon of thy handmaid, thou haſt looſed my bonds;</hi> I am doubly thy ſervant, both by birth and redemption, thy creature, thy captive. This is the reall effect of thankſgiving.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. For the extent of its matter.</note> 4. Finally, <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> is tranſcendent for the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and <hi>extent</hi> of its <hi>matter.</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. v. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>In every thing give thanks;</hi> for all, that is <hi>in</hi> God, and for all that cometh <hi>from</hi> God. <note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 119. v. 68.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou art good, and doeſt good,</hi> and every good thing is matter of praiſe: as, Firſt, all his <hi>ſpirituall</hi> mercies, <note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 1. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly things,</hi> in Chriſt; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he doth reckon up <hi>particulars:</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">v. 4.</note> Election, <note n="b" place="margin">v. 5.</note> Adoption, <note n="c" place="margin">v. 7.</note> Redemption and forgiveneſſe, <note n="d" place="margin">v. 11.</note> an inheritance, with the <note n="e" place="margin">v. 13.</note> ſealing and <note n="f" place="margin">v. 14.</note> earneſt thereof. And all this <note n="g" place="margin">v. 6.12.</note> to <hi>the praiſe of the glory of his grace.</hi> Secondly, all his <note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 16. v. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>creating</hi> and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiall mercies. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelfe, even the wicked for the day of evill.</hi> All creatures ſhall bee for the praiſe of his mercy or juſtice, every tree ſhall ſerve him for fruit or firing, every head ſhall give its milke, fleece, or fleſh. <note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 14. v. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>I will get me honour upon Pharaoh.</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Ioſh. 7. v. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>My ſonne, give glory to God.</hi> Yea, all his <hi>works</hi> in heaven and earth they are <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116550:13"/>for this ſervice, they were made for this <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 148.</note> 
                     <hi>end.</hi> There is a ſhort <hi>Pſalme,</hi> that doth containe a <hi>Syſteme</hi> or Epitome of the whole <hi>Creation,</hi> which is there ſeverally called upon for this duty: the <hi>top</hi> or higheſt round of that ladder doth reach to the higheſt heaven, the foot ſtandeth upon the earth below. Let us ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly runne it up, it beginneth <note n="m" place="margin">ver. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Hallelujah Hallelujah,</hi> firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon them in <hi>heaven,</hi> where there are <hi>three ſtories;</hi> In the firſt, <note n="n" place="margin">v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Angels;</hi> in the ſecond, <note n="o" place="margin">v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Starres;</hi> in the third, which is the <note n="p" place="margin">v. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>heaven</hi> of <hi>heavens,</hi> 
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Coeli Coelorum dicuntur in fimi Coeli, ut ſervus ſervorum eſt infimus &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectiſſimus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus. Foord ad loc.</note> below, there are the clouds. And all theſe are ſummoned to <note n="r" place="margin">v. 5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>praiſe the Lord.</hi> Next all on <note n="ſ" place="margin">v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>earth</hi> are called upon; all <note n="t" place="margin">v. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> Elements, meteors, places, plants, living creatures, fiſh, beaſts, fowl, reaſonable creatures, high &amp; low, young &amp; old, men &amp; women, that is, all ranks, ages, ſexes. In ſhort, as <hi>faith</hi> hath promiſes and experiences as its ground: <hi>feare</hi> hath threatnings: <hi>Love</hi> hath all that is lovely: ſo every <hi>good thing</hi> is <hi>matter</hi> of praiſe, yea all theſe and every other <note n="u" place="margin">Coloſ. 2. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>grace.</hi> Hence the purblind <note n="x" place="margin">Haec eſt enim una virtus non ſolum maxima ſed etiam mater virtutum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um reliquarum. Quid eſt pietas niſi voluntas grata in paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp;c. Cicer. pro C. Plancio.</note> 
                     <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, that this one <hi>virtue</hi> (virtue was grace with him) is not onely the <hi>greateſt,</hi> but the <hi>mother</hi> of all the reſt: <q rend="margQuotes">for what is <hi>piety</hi> (ſaith he) but a <hi>thankfull</hi> heart towards ones parents? Who are good <hi>Patriots,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>mindefull</hi> of the kindneſſe of their Country towards them? Who is <hi>holy,</hi> but he which payeth his <hi>thankes</hi> unto the gods?</q> Yea this <hi>duty-grace,</hi> ſhould runne through all our very <hi>naturall</hi> actions too. <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> 
                     <hi>Whether therefore yee eate or drink or whatſoever you do, do all to the glory of God.</hi> Nay &amp; through all our actions, ſpeeches <hi>in generall,</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Coloſ. 3.17</note> 
                     <hi>And whatſoever yee doe in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, giving thanks unto God and the Father by him.</hi> There is yet a more full expreſſion from the ſame Apoſtle; <note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Giving thanks alwayes, for all things, unto God.</hi> And good reaſon, ſo long as there is a promiſe that <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 28. Application. 1. Reproof.</note> 
                     <hi>All things ſhall worke together for good to them that love God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then, Firſt, I muſt take leave to <hi>reprove</hi> all that are <hi>enemies</hi> or <hi>backe friends</hi> to this <hi>duty,</hi> and to tell them from <hi>God;</hi> that he taketh their ingratitude for a <hi>diſhonour</hi> to himſelfe: To tell them from <hi>nature</hi> and the very heathens, that their ſinne is too bad for a <note n="a" place="margin">Ingratum dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris, omnia. dixeris.</note> name; it is the <note n="b" place="margin">In quo vitio nibil mali non in eſt liceco</note> Epitome of all ſinne. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116550:13"/>that I may ſpeake <hi>diſtinctly</hi> and juſtly, there are <hi>two</hi> ſorts of <hi>Offenders</hi> that muſt here beare a reproofe.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. To malignant enemies.</note> I. Such as out of meere <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> and <hi>malignity,</hi> are <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to our thankſgivings; ſuch profeſſed <hi>Antipodes,</hi> to whom our high Noone, is a midnight; that <note n="c" place="margin">Lam. 1. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>mocke</hi> at theſe our <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> and like that ſcornfull <hi>daughter</hi> of King <hi>Saul,</hi> doe <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 9. v. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>looke thorough</hi> their <hi>windowes</hi> upon theſe dayes, and <hi>deſpiſe us in their heart for dancing before the Lord with all our might.</hi> But let all ſuch <hi>Michals</hi> know, that <note n="e" place="margin">ver. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>It is before the Lord which choſe us before them and their party,</hi> and therefore wee will <hi>play before the Lord, and will be yet more vile then thus;</hi> yet at laſt, ſhal we be in honour, whilſt perhaps their forces and hopes ſhall goe with <hi>barren wombes</hi> and <hi>dry breaſts</hi> unto their graves. I confeſſe the ſpirit of <hi>ungratefull malignity</hi> is now riſen to that height in theſe parts, that it is ſcarcely an act of greater valour to <hi>get a victory,</hi> then to dare <hi>keep a thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> for it. I have heard that in France, the Papiſts do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all as <hi>Huguenots</hi> and Heretiques that do praiſe God by <hi>ſinging of Pſalmes,</hi> which is in our language to ſay that a <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> and a <hi>Puritan</hi> are both one: ſhall we come up to that degree?</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But <hi>what</hi> may be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of ſuch an horrid ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſpirit of blaſphemous <hi>ingratitude?</hi> What ayles the ſcorners?</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> 
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Surely it is the abounding of <hi>unholineſſe</hi> that cauſeth this aboundance of <hi>ingratitude,</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">ver. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Vnthankfull,</hi> and <hi>unholy,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> do uſually goe together. And this is obſervable, that the more of <hi>Devill</hi> there is in any man, the greater enemy is that man to all holy praiſes; yea Satan himſelfe is not ſo much inraged againſt any or all duties of the Saints, as againſt their Thankſgivings. He can better beare their prayers, faſtings, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, readings, becauſe he knoweth whilſt they are at theſe, they are but begging, plowing or ſowing; but when they are prayſing he knoweth they have then received their almes, and are <hi>returning home bringing their ſheaves with them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2"> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. But the enemies have their <hi>pretences</hi> of reaſon, nay, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, inducing them to abhor this duty they ſay; let us heare and anſwer them.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116550:14"/>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> Our <hi>victories</hi> (ſay they) are but <hi>lies</hi> and deluſions, they are mockings of of God and men, and therefore intolerable.</p>
                  <p n="1"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> 1. Doth not this language runne well like that of <hi>Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keh?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 18.28.</note> then <hi>Rabſhakeh ſtood and cryed with a loud voyce, Let not Hezekiah deceive you &amp;c.</hi> But</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If it bee <hi>falſe,</hi> why are you ſo <hi>troubled,</hi> impatient, inraged? Surely we gather that you do ſecretly <hi>beleeve</hi> our newes even whilſt you cry it downe for lies. <hi>Divines</hi> ſay, that one good argument againſt Atheiſts, which pretend they beleeve there is no God, is their owne continuall <hi>clamours, diſputings,</hi> and railings againſt the Deity; which ſeeme to argue ſome ſecret he ſitations and doubting qualmes in their owne ſpirits con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that point.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The trueth is, men <hi>will not know,</hi> nor beleeve, nor ſee, the truth of our good tidings and ſucceſſes; <hi>Theſe things they are willingly ignorant of,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.3.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of his ſcoffers. And becauſe they are wilfull, and as I conceive abſent, I ſhall ſpend no more time upon them; but doe onely deſire to ſend them a <hi>Token</hi> by ſome <hi>Neuter</hi> or other (for theſe two are much together) whom I deſire to turne downe a leafe, and to ſhew it them at next meeting, <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Let favour be ſhewed to the wicked, yet will he not learn righteouſneſſe:</hi> The men confeſſe they have received more favour at our hands then ever we ſhould have found at theirs: But doth this worke upon them? No, <hi>In the Land of uprightneſſe will he deale unjuſtly, and will not behold the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the Lord.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up</hi> (whether to ſtrike or beare the Banner) <hi>they will not ſee.</hi> Marke, the defect, the fault, is not in their heads or eyes, but in their hearts, and wills, and there is no argument ſo fit to confute we <hi>will not,</hi> as, <hi>you ſhall; But they ſhall ſee;</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 10.13.</note> 
                     <hi>a rod for the backs of fooles) they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed for their envy at the people,</hi> or towards the people, yea, <hi>the fire of thine enemies ſhall devoure thom:</hi> That is, as <note n="b" place="margin">Iudg. 8.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Gideon taught</hi> the Neutrall and Malignant men of <hi>Succoth with briers and thorns of the wilderneſſe;</hi> ſo the Lord will teach and convince theſe men, by <hi>devouring fire</hi> at laſt, if they will not ſee by its light, they ſhall feele its heat. And becauſe ſome bitter, <hi>winking</hi> enemies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116550:14"/>will beleeve none other arguments: let us leave them to the Lords convictions, and to the <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Hippoc. Sect.</hi> 8 <hi>Apbor.</hi> 6. Amos 7. v. 4. Ezek. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. v. 13. Object. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Aphoriſme</hi> of the great phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian which ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">what things ſoever medicins doe not cure, thoſe Iron cureth; what Iron doth not cure, that fire cureth; what fire doth not cure, thoſe things are to be judged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable.</q> God hath tryed to heale the land, and eſpecially our enemies, by his word and by his ſword in our firſt warre, and now he <hi>contendeth by fire,</hi> that is, by ſharper, cleerer, works and diſcoveries then ever; and if this will not doe, woe unto them for incurable. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filuhineſſe any more, till I cauſe my fury to reſt upon thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> your victories <hi>true</hi> as you report them, (ſay they) yet wee will not, cannot joyne to give <hi>thanks</hi> unto God for the <hi>ſhedding</hi> of <hi>bloud,</hi> and for the <hi>killing of men?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Give mee leave to anſwer theſe, as Chriſt did thoſe Jewes, <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 21. v. 24.</note> with ſome other Queſtions.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> Firſt; <hi>Canſt thou reade? haſt</hi> thou a <hi>Bible?</hi> (for this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the objection of the illiterate and profane perſon) then <hi>turne</hi> to a place or two, and thou ſhalt ſee what Gods Spirit and Saints have ſaid, and done in this caſe. <note n="e" place="margin">Iudg. 5. v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord for avenging of Iſrael, when the people willingly offered themſelves.</hi> This thankſgiving was by authority, <note place="margin">Ver. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Then ſang Deborah and Baruk on that day ſaying.</hi> Yet that day of a ſong, was a day of much bloud, to <hi>Siſera</hi> and all his hoſt.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> But the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> and open <hi>enemies;</hi> we fight againſt our owne Country men and neighbours.</p>
                  <p n="1"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> 1. <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10. v. 36.37.</note> He that ſheweth no mercy he is the veryeſt ſtranger. 2. Thoſe <hi>Canaanites</hi> had been <note n="g" place="margin">Iud. 1. v. 4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>conquered</hi> by <hi>Iſrael</hi> before; but for <hi>Iſraels ſinnes,</hi> and through their owne <hi>treacheries,</hi> were growne conſiderable againe, yea and <note n="h" place="margin">cap. 4. v. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>mightily oppreſſed</hi> them, wherefore <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth fight and breake them the ſecond time, and bleſſeth the Lord for their victories over them, and his vengeance upon them. Nay, the Spirit of God elſewhere doth warrant, promiſe, command, ſuch thankſgivings: <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 58. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall reioyce when he ſeeth the vengeance, hee ſhall waſh his feet in the bloud of the wicked.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3"> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>Who is it</hi> that doth <hi>ſhed bloud,</hi> and <hi>kill m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n?</hi> The Aſſayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116550:15"/>or the defendants? they that offend us, or we that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves? what, when a ſort of men have beene <hi>beaten</hi> and conquered the firſt time, and being conquered have <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> many confeſſed favours from their Conquerors; have <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,</hi> covenanted, ſworne (thereupon) never more to <hi>beare Armes</hi> againſt them, were ſuffered to live <hi>peaceably</hi> amongſt them; but after all this doe rebelliouſly, ingratefully, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, ariſe in armes, ſurpriſe Caſtles, cut the throats of them that were <hi>quiet in the Land;</hi> and are by Gods juſt juſtice and immediate hand diſappointed, cut off in battell a ſecond time: Will you call this a <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Qui jubet, is facit ſcelus.</hi> Sence.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhedding of bloud,</hi> and a <hi>killing of men,</hi> for which the Lord muſt not be praiſed? Is <hi>ſelfe-defence</hi> to be called <hi>murther?</hi> or <hi>execution</hi> of juſtice to be accounted <hi>man-ſlaughter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doe but looke I pray you impartially and ſeriouſly upon thoſe famous <hi>examples</hi> and proceedings of wiſeſt <hi>Solomon</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Adonijah</hi> his elder brother; and ſay, have we not uſed theſe men as brethren? <note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 1. v. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Adonijah</hi> had committed a <hi>firſt fault,</hi> in uſurping the kingdom in his fathers life time, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> was pardoned by <hi>Solomon,</hi> upon a condition, or with a proviſo, <note place="margin">Ver. 52, 53.</note> 
                     <hi>If he will ſhew himſelfe a worthy man, there ſhall not an haire of him fall to the earth; but if wickedneſſe be found in him, he ſhall die.</hi> And he is ſent away with this condition. After this, <hi>Adonijah</hi> is found <hi>faulty again,</hi> at leaſt in a cloſe plodding pernicious <hi>deſigne,</hi> to the old end: Hee would have <hi>Abiſhag</hi> the <hi>Shunamite</hi> to be given to him to wife. <note place="margin">1 King. 2. v. 15. 16, &amp;c. Ver. 22, 23, 24, 25. Ver. 26, 27.</note> For this ſecond attempt hee dyeth. Yea and ſome of his <hi>old complices</hi> doe fall with him, though it is not expreſt that they had their hands in this ſecond deſigne. <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar</hi> the Prieſt, hee is <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> and <hi>ejected</hi> out of his place, though hee hath his life given him for <hi>former</hi> good ſervices. And <hi>Joabs</hi> old crimes, <note place="margin">Ver. 32, 33.</note> they are remembred and puniſhed. It is worth the while, to repeat the <hi>grounds,</hi> upon which <hi>Solomon</hi> proceedeth againſt them. <hi>Fall upon him,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>that thou mayeſt take away the innocent bloud which</hi> Joab <hi>ſhed, from me, and from the houſe of my Father, and the Lord ſhall returne his bloud upon his owne head, who fell upon two men more righteous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116550:15"/>and better then hee, &amp;c.</hi> Laſtly, rayling <hi>Shimei,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 42, 43, 44.</note> commeth to an account, and juſtice findeth him out in his old age, by his owne help and directions, becauſe he <hi>kept not the oath of the Lord,</hi> and the commandement that <hi>Solomon</hi> had charged him with. Now tell me, O thou adverſary of our Thankſgiving dayes, <hi>how much</hi> doe the crimes of our vanquiſhed enemies <hi>exceed</hi> thoſe of <hi>Adonijah, Abiathar, Joab, Shimei?</hi> And how much is the mercy of our State above the ſeverity of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>For whoſe bloud ſhed?</hi> For what killing of men art thou ſo <hi>offended?</hi> Surely, it is becauſe it was the bloud of Malignants, becauſe it was not the <hi>Round-heads</hi> bloud: For had <hi>that party,</hi> which is beaten, gotten the day upon us; had they ſlaine thouſands of ours, for hundreds of theirs, then thou wouldeſt have <hi>given thankes</hi> with a witneſſe, even thankes <hi>for killing</hi> of men and ſhedding of bloud: thou wouldeſt have kept ſuch a revell or wake for it, as all the <hi>tenne Commandements</hi> ſhould have been ſacrificed by thee for a <hi>thank-offering.</hi> Away, away, with this <hi>groſſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi> God knowes thy heart, and man may ſee thee, though thou winkeſt.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, <hi>It is not</hi> (God is our record, it is not) for bloudſhed and killing of men (to ſpeak properly) that we give thankes: but for the <hi>proſperity</hi> of the Lords cauſe, for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the bloud of his ſervants; tis for a further ſtep towards <hi>peace</hi> and ſettlement, by removing implacable impediments out of the way of a full deliverance and reformation, men who now let, and will let. Shall a <hi>Robber</hi> on the way, <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. v. 7.</note> fall upon me for my <hi>purſe and life,</hi> ſo that nothing but the loſſe of his bloud, can bee the ſecurity of mine: and muſt I not <hi>give thankes</hi> for mine owne deliverance if I beate him? Wee are wholly, unqueſtionably <hi>defenſive</hi> in this ſecond war.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. To male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented friends:</note> II. There is <hi>another ſort</hi> of perſons, which though <hi>friends</hi> and brethren, in the maine <hi>common cauſe;</hi> yet through ſome <hi>diſſatisfaction,</hi> diſcontent, offence, or jealoſies, are <hi>no friends to</hi> ſo <hi>much victory,</hi> but are ſlow and <hi>cold</hi> at our <hi>Thanksgivings;</hi> nay (perhaps) doe <hi>look</hi> but <hi>ſowrely</hi> and <hi>ſuſpectingly</hi> upon ſuch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116550:16"/>as on theſe dayes, doe <hi>dance before the LORD with all their might.</hi> I remember ſome Auncients <note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſtome. Auſtine. Lactantins.</note> did condemne thoſe for <hi>Heretickes,</hi> that held there were <hi>Antipodes,</hi> that is, people inhabiting the earth juſt underneath, and diametrally oppoſite to us. <hi>Brethren,</hi> I beſeech you, let us not come to that degree of ignorance and <hi>diſingenuity,</hi> as to account all men Erroneous that are hearty and hot in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that we have direct <hi>Antipodes,</hi> I meane (in plaine Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh) that <hi>declare</hi> lowdly to the world that there are many mighty bitter <hi>oppoſites</hi> and Malignants; and doe <hi>act</hi> againſt them to their uttermoſt both in <hi>prayers &amp; praiſes.</hi> Let me have leave to deale freely this day, eſpecially with our <hi>owne friends.</hi> Are there not many, very many amongſt us, which are like a <hi>man condemned,</hi> upon the Gibbet, ready to be preſently <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,</hi> one commeth to him and offereth him a <hi>Ladder</hi> to come downe by, and ſave his life: but he ſtandeth <hi>ſcrupling,</hi> obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, doubting, whether the Ladder be firme or no, whether the <hi>rounds</hi> be faſt or looſe, whether they may not deceive him, or breake under him, and ſo indanger a fall? yea, but O man, O friend, what will become of thy neck if thou <hi>ſtayeſt there?</hi> Or by what other way canſt, wilt, wouldeſt thou come down? I hope not willingly by the rope? Honourable Senators, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my <hi>plainneſſe,</hi> and take me <hi>ſeriouſly,</hi> the <hi>neck</hi> of every thorough-godly well affected man in <hi>England</hi> is now <hi>in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and the breaking or ſaving of it depends upon the <hi>come-off,</hi> in which, the <hi>rounds,</hi> or nothing, muſt ſave us. Beware therefore, how wee grow ſhy or ſullen at any neceſſary law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>meanes</hi> of ſelfe-preſervation, and ſo <note n="a" place="margin">Jon. 2. v. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>forſake our owne mercies.</hi> Let us therefore <hi>put on our wedding garments,</hi> and <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Non poteſt autem quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam &amp; invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as agere: quia invidere, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentis &amp; moeſii est; gratias a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, gaudentis.</hi> Sen. de Benef. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> countenances when providence doth invite us to feaſt; And beware, leſt when we pretend to avoyd <hi>Schiſmaticall Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings,</hi> wee runne our ſelves over on the other hand, into a kinde of <hi>Orthodoxe ingratitude.</hi> For mine own part, farre be it from mee, to pleade for the <hi>extravagancies</hi> of any ſort of inſtruments. I beleeve we have <hi>all</hi> had our great and ſpeciall <hi>opportunities</hi> and ſeaſons of doing much good for God, and have <hi>all neglected</hi> to improve them. Nay, perhaps wee have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116550:16"/>then <hi>ſacrificed his</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Hoſ. 2. v. 5, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Corne, Wine, Wooll and Flax unto our owne</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Hab. 1. v. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>nets and drags,</hi> and I am deceived if God doth not take us up and <hi>ſcourge</hi> us of all <hi>ſides,</hi> for it, and for our ſelfe-<hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions:</hi> perhaps upon the backs of <hi>one another.</hi> And then, O we ſhall be willing like fighting <hi>School-boys,</hi> to <hi>forgive</hi> each other, if our Maſter would forgive us. I ſay it againe, that all our ſelviſh <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Kids fleſh</hi> will bee eaten with bitter herbs: and our <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 27. v. 2, 6. compared with chap. 30. ver. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ziglags</hi> will bee but as <hi>new peeces in old garments:</hi> And perhaps our <note n="e" place="margin">1 Acts 15. v. 39, 40. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Paroxyſmes</hi> may make us walke for it as farre as <hi>America,</hi> as it was with <hi>pettiſh Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this is not the way of amendment or compoſure, to fall out with our meate, and to caſt it from us, or to bee ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len towards the Lord when hee ſmileth upon us with delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</p>
                  <p>I reade one example of ſuch an <hi>April-Thanksgiving</hi> for a great victory in Scripture: which gives us divers proper paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and ſerious Obſervations. It was when <note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Generall Joab</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> Army under his command, had ſlaine <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and beaten the unnaturall Army that was with him. 'Tis ſaid, <note n="g" place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>The victory that day was turned into mourning unto all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for the people heard ſay that day, how the King was grieved for his ſonne: <note n="h" place="margin">Ver. 3.</note> And the people got them by ſtealth that day into the Citie, as people being aſhamed ſteale away when they flee in battell.</hi> Here was a ſtrange kinde of victory and <hi>Thank giving</hi> indeed, conſidering the greatneſſe of the mercy received. But marke we upon it, (out of the ſame ſtory) both its cauſe, and conſequents.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. The Cauſe.</note> 1. The principall <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> unſeaſonable ſadneſſe was his too much <hi>good will</hi> and affections to the <hi>enemie.</hi> The <note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Plurima bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia continet patria, &amp; eſt antiquior pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, quam is, qui ut ajunt, creaverit.</hi> Cicer Fragment.</note> 
                     <hi>father</hi> (in him) was too hard for the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate love toward a <hi>ſon,</hi> ſwallowed up that publike juſtice du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to a <hi>Malefactor.</hi> Are there ſome of the <hi>right party,</hi> nay and <hi>good men</hi> too ſicke of that dangerous diſeaſe? very <hi>heathens</hi> ſhall riſe in judgment againſt them. Gallant <hi>Brutus</hi> thou didſt publikely ſcourge, and then ſlay thine owne ſons for attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to re-inſlave the Common-wealth!</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</note> 2. The <hi>conſequents</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> unſeaſonable ſadneſſe are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe: as, </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116550:17"/>
                  <p n="1"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſequent. </seg>1</label> 1. The <hi>Anſwer</hi> or high ſpeech of Generall <hi>Ioab</hi> you muſt allow, for the Souldier, the Courtier, and the kinſman, in his expreſſions, for he threatneth, he ſweareth, he chideth. We will looke onely into the matter. <note place="margin">ver. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou haſt ſhamed this day, the faces of all thy ſervants, which this day have ſaved thy life, and the lives of thy ſonnes, and of thy daughters, and the lives of thy wives,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver 6.</note> 
                     <hi>and the lives of thy concubines. In that thou loveſt thine enemies and hateſt thy friends, for thou haſt declared this day, that thou regardeſt neither Princes nor ſervants, for this day I perceive, that if Abſolom had lived and all we had dyed this day,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>then it had pleaſed thee well. Now therefore ariſe, goe forth and ſpeake comfortably unto thy ſervants, for I ſweare by the Lord, if thou goe not forth, there will not tarry one with thee this night, and this will be worſe unto thee, then all the evill that befell thee from thy youth untill now.</hi> This bold ſpeech needeth no <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but there is in it a great deale of <hi>Marſhall politiques;</hi> out of which a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may draw many prudent and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inſtructions. You have read the ſtory of thoſe three Brethren, the <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Immaturum virginisamorem ultus eſt ferro, citavere leges nefas: ſed abſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit virtus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricidam, &amp; fa cinus intra glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam fuit &amp;c.</hi> Flor. lib. 1. ca. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Horatii,</hi> how the <hi>ſiſter</hi> of the ſurviving Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, weeping to ſee the ſpoyls of her lover (but an enemy) upon her Brother, was paid with bloud for her tears. The fact I confeſſe, was horrid in that Victor, but it may teach us that the ſlighting of our deliverance is a dangerous provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to neereſt friends.</p>
                  <p n="2"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſequent. </seg>2</label> 2. Obſerve wee in that ſadneſſe of <hi>David,</hi> the perilous <hi>animoſities</hi> ariſing between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> about bringing home the King. <note place="margin">ver. 9, 10. ver. 41. ver. 42.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſrael</hi> chargeth <hi>Iudah</hi> with <hi>King-ſtealing,</hi> Why have our brethren, the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſtollen thee away? <hi>Iudah</hi> claymeth <hi>kindred</hi> in <hi>David</hi> and bearing themſelves high upon that relation, they endeavor to <hi>purge themſelves</hi> from taking any gifts, profits, places, for their ſervice. And at laſt, the great <hi>quarrel</hi> is, <note place="margin">ver. 43.</note> who hath the moſt ſhare in the King and ſhould have the principall hand in bringing him back. A <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> that had like to have coſt them dearer then all the wars before.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſequent. </seg>3</label> The third conſequent that floweth from that <hi>weeping thanksgiving,</hi> and this royall <hi>contention,</hi> is an <hi>advantage</hi> taken
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116550:17"/>from both thoſe by the <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.1.</note> 
                     <hi>common enemy</hi> one of the old <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> party. <hi>And there happened to bee there a man af Belial, whoſe name was Sheba the ſonne of Bichri, a Benjamite.</hi> Marke it well; The man was one of <hi>Sauls</hi> owne Tribe; ſome thinke, a <hi>Prince</hi> of that Tribe, becauſe they followed him ſo readily, yea and it is conceived, he was of the <note n="a" place="margin">Pet. Martyr.</note> 
                     <hi>kindred</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> and was never well affected to <hi>David,</hi> and therefore now, hee blew a trumpet and ſaid, <hi>We have no part in David &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 2.</note> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he was univerſally <hi>followed,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> wholly <hi>forſaken.</hi> See, <hi>ſelfe-diviſion</hi> is the next way to ſet up the <hi>old common</hi> Enemy againe, and to bring downe the <hi>Kite</hi> upon the <hi>Mouſe</hi> and <hi>Frog.</hi> which may ſweepe away both, whilſt they are a fighting. <hi>Away therefore</hi> with all <hi>ſullenneſſe</hi> and ſelfe-diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all yee that are truly godly, well affected and throughly ingaged in this common cauſe againſt the common Enemy, whatſoever diſcontents, provocations, injuries you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from one another. Suffer not any <hi>Gangrenes</hi> to ſtrike to your wounds, for that will be <hi>noyſome</hi> indeed to others, but <hi>mortall</hi> to your ſelves, and to that good <hi>old godly Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> with which we muſt all now ſinke or ſwim. <hi>Revenge</hi> ſheweth me to be a <hi>man,</hi> but forgiving to be a <hi>chriſtian;</hi> that, makes me <hi>even</hi> with mine enemy, but this, ſets me <note n="b" place="margin">See Pro. 20.3. Eccleſ. 10.4.</note> 
                     <hi>above</hi> him; that may be juſt, but this is ſurely truely honourable. <note n="c" place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Ariſtidis.</note> O that <hi>carriage</hi> and <hi>language</hi> of <hi>Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> was <hi>truely noble,</hi> of which we reade in the ſtory; <hi>Ariſtides</hi> by the furtherance of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> had been <hi>baniſhed</hi> from <hi>Athens</hi> by the law of <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi> for tenne years; but within three years he was <hi>recalled</hi> againe becauſe <hi>Xerxes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> was come with a vaſt <hi>Army</hi> into <hi>Attica;</hi> after <hi>Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> his returne, <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> is choſen the only <hi>Lieutenant Generall</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> (notwithſtanding all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer paſſages) doth alwayes <hi>faithfully aid</hi> and aſſiſt him in all things, as well with his travell as with his Counſell, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wan his <hi>enemie</hi> great honour, but greater to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> for he adventured through the midſt of the <hi>enemies ſhips</hi> in the night, and with great danger got from <hi>Aegina</hi> to <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> tent, and calling him out thus beſpake him. <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116550:18"/>we are both <hi>wiſe,</hi> it is high time we ſhould now leave off this vaine <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>ſpite</hi> we have long time borne each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we ſhould enter into <hi>another</hi> ſort of <hi>envy</hi> more honourable and profitable for both: I meane, <hi>which of</hi> us two ſhould doe his <hi>beſt</hi> indeavour to ſave <hi>Greece:</hi> you by ruling and <hi>commanding;</hi> and I by <hi>counſelling,</hi> &amp;c.</q> How cleerly hath this poore heathen taught us chriſtians to <note n="d" place="margin">Privatas ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitias Reipub. ignoſcere.</note> bury all our perſonall quarrels in the <hi>wounds</hi> of the publike Enemy? Well, my Brethren, deceive not your ſelves with dreames, if you are godly indeed, you <hi>may</hi> agree, you <hi>muſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and I dare tell you that (at laſt) you <hi>ſhall</hi> agree, either as fellow <hi>Conquerours,</hi> if you pleaſe, or as <hi>fellow priſoners,</hi> if you will ſtill be ſullen; the dogs ſhall <hi>drive you</hi> together, or <hi>eate you</hi> ſeverally. Oh do but unite ſo neere in <hi>affections</hi> as you are united in <hi>dangers,</hi> and you have <hi>undone the Devill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>2</label> Secondly, We have hence a <hi>leſſon of praiſes,</hi> it is worded for us by King <hi>David,</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 34.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>My ſoule ſhall make her boaſt in the Lord, the humble ſhall heare and beglad. O magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together.</hi> Magnifie him we ſhould for ſpirituall mercies, and for temporall, for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and for particular, for former and for preſent favours; all theſe, yea, all our Parliament mercies would require the <hi>volumes</hi> of a <hi>Thuanus</hi> or <hi>Baronius,</hi> rather then this <hi>peece</hi> of a Sermon to ſet them forth. But I hope you have pennes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about that ſubject all this while: I hope you have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſome <hi>Committee</hi> to audite the Debenters of the <hi>Lord of your hoſts,</hi> aſwell as of the ſouldiers. And let me have leave to tell you here (in a ſeaſonable <hi>parentheſis</hi>) that ſuch <hi>Records</hi> are acts of Juſtice, for Gratitude is a branch of the Law of nature: They are acts of <hi>Religion,</hi> for herein wee <hi>honour God,</hi> as in my Text, and then he hath <note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> bound himſelfe to <hi>honour us:</hi> They are acts of <hi>prudence</hi> and policy, for they doe knit a <hi>knot</hi> upon the mercie received that it ravels not out againe; and in that knot they have a <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vetus benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium comemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando, invitas novum.</hi> Senec.</note> 
                     <hi>hooke</hi> by which they catch in future mercies. <hi>Tamerlaine</hi> asked of <hi>Bajazet,</hi> when he had taken him priſoner, in battell, whether or no he ever had been <hi>thankfull</hi> to God for making him an <hi>Emperour?</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116550:18"/>He anſwered freely, he never thought upon that matter in all his life. <hi>Tamerlaine</hi> replyeth, And why ſhould God make you, a man that hath but <hi>one eye,</hi> to be King of the <hi>Turkes?</hi> and me, a man <hi>lame</hi> in one leg, King of the <hi>Tattars,</hi> above all other men? No mervaile if thou, being ſo unthankfull, haſt loſt ſo great a Battell. Thankfulneſſe is the way to bring in <hi>more:</hi> and therefore, though I cannot lanch out, into this <hi>Sea</hi> of all our mercies, yet I would, I muſt fiſh in the <hi>river</hi> of <hi>this dayes ſalvation.</hi> May it pleaſe you to lend mee your hearts but for halfe an houre, I ſhall endeavour to warm them and returne them backe to you againe, when I have given you ſome ſpeciall peculiar <hi>Obſervations</hi> upon the mercies and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories of this dayes praiſe, and have ſet up a <hi>triumphant pillar,</hi> though but of <hi>bricke,</hi> like that aſcribed to <hi>Noahs</hi> ſonnes, to tell poſterity <hi>what the Lord hath done for your ſoules.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obſervation. 1. upon the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of this day.</note> 1. Conſider the <hi>number,</hi> the <hi>multitude,</hi> of this dayes <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> They are the faireſt and greateſt cluſter of mercies, (ſo farre as I can finde or remember) that ever the Lord gave you at once. <hi>A cluſter</hi> like that at <hi>Eſchol,</hi> which the Spirit of God thus recordeth; <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 13. ver. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>And they came to the brook of</hi> Eſchol, <hi>and cut downe from thence a branch, with one cluſter of grapes, and the bare it betweene</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Viz. <hi>Ioſue &amp; caleb. Sic aijt</hi> Ambr.</note> 
                     <hi>two upon a ſtaffe; and they brought of the Pomegranats and of the figs.</hi> This was a good <hi>earneſt</hi> of their neerneſſe unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> and of the goodneſſe of that land. Why may not our Cluſter be ſomewhat a like <hi>token</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us <hi>for good,</hi> even of a ſpeedy entrance into an happy ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement? This is the <hi>day</hi> of the <hi>Cluſter.</hi> I obſerve that the <hi>enemy,</hi> in this <hi>ſecond warre,</hi> hath never (hitherto) brought forth <hi>ſingle</hi> births, but multitudes, <hi>Gads, troopes,</hi> of inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, revolts, ſurpriſals, at once. It is obſerved by <hi>Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> that your <hi>vileſt</hi> and venomeſt creatures, doe bring forth moſt frequently, moſt <hi>numerouſly;</hi> as Rats, Mice, Serpents; whereas the <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Partus Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantinus.</hi> Adag.</note> 
                     <hi>Elephant</hi> is ſome years breeding, and the Royall <hi>Lion</hi> brings forth but one or two at a birth. Surely, our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies grow more venomous and more verminous now in their attempts, plots, aſſaults: For this day wee celebrate delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances from a numerous iſſue of miſchiefes. Your owne <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116550:19"/>for this day, that toucheth but generalls, calleth for a <hi>ſix ſtringed inſtrument;</hi> it mentioneth a parcell of no leſſe then <hi>ſixe common-places</hi> of danger and deliverance. No mervaile if the enemy did never <hi>rage more againſt</hi> any one day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving then againſt this, I have found the cauſe of their fury: never were they ſo <hi>manifoldly</hi> beaten, in ſo many places, plots, attempts at once, as this day recordeth. The following obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations will expreſſe ſome of the particulars; Meane while, let this firſt be <hi>crowned</hi> with that bleſſing, <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 68.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord who daily loadeth us with his benefits, even the God of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Selah.</p>
                  <p n="2"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>2</label> 2. Obſerve the <hi>univerſality</hi> and <hi>ſpreadings</hi> of this dayes dangers and deliverances. The <hi>garment</hi> of <hi>gladneſſe</hi> reacheth over all the <hi>Quarters</hi> of the Land. It is not onely for ſome Northerne, or Southerne, for ſome Eaſterne or Weſterne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that we now give thankes: but the <hi>Robe</hi> reacheth from <hi>Cocquet-water</hi> in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> to <hi>Horſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> in the <hi>South:</hi> there is its <hi>latitude.</hi> From <hi>Dover-Caſtle</hi> and all Kent in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> to <hi>Penſands,</hi> the utmoſt part of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt:</hi> there is its <hi>longitude.</hi> Beſides all the <hi>Inland victories,</hi> all over the kingdome, with which this <hi>Robe</hi> is poudred throughout; to wit, in the Counties of <hi>Weſtmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Northumberland,</hi> Biſhopwrick, <hi>Yorke</hi> (both City and County) <hi>Nottingham, Lincolne, Rutland, Huntington, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Norfolke,</hi> and <hi>Norwich, Suffolke, Cheſhire, Hereford, Worceſter, &amp;c.</hi> Both North and South Wales, <hi>Kent, Suſſex, Surrey, Middleſex,</hi> and Weſt-ward even unto <hi>Cornwall.</hi> Crowne this, with that interjection. <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 107. v. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh give thankes unto the Lord, for he is gracious: Let the redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the Enemy, from the Eaſt and from the Weſt, from the North and from the South,</hi> the oyle of gladneſſe hath <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 233. v. 2.</note> run down like the ointment of <hi>Aaron,</hi> from the head to the hem.</p>
                  <p n="3"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>3</label> 3. Obſerve we the <hi>ſecrecy,</hi> treachery, and ſlineſſe of our dangers, and thence, the greatneſſe of our <hi>deliverance.</hi> In the firſt war the common enemy, had in him more of the <hi>Beare</hi> and <hi>Lyon,</hi> he did roare and bark when he would bite, did <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116550:19"/>himſelfe</hi> an open and armed Enemy: But now, in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond war, he hath more in him of the <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Serpent;</hi> he cries, <hi>Peace,</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 55. v. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>peace, when war is in his heart.</hi> Their preſent hoſtilities have in them more of the <hi>Powder Treaſon</hi> than of <hi>Eighty eight;</hi> more of a <hi>Maſſacre</hi> than a <hi>war.</hi> They ſeem to ſay now in this <hi>ſecond Edition,</hi> as <hi>Sanballat</hi> and the reſt with him, againſt <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> and his party; <note n="d" place="margin">Neh. 4. v. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>They ſhall not know, neither ſee, till wee come in the midſt among them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the work to ceaſe.</hi> How many <hi>mines</hi> of ſurpriſes, revolts, inſurrections, had they prepared ready to ſpring and <hi>play</hi> in all parts of the Land (yea and of the Sea too) at once? Onely the Lord he did <hi>countermine</hi> them whilſt wee thought not of it. Yea, had not the Lord confounded their language, ſo that they could not <hi>time it</hi> exactly as they intended, they might have <hi>ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us up quicke.</hi> But the truth is, they marred their <hi>muſicke</hi> by <hi>ill-timing</hi> it. It was with them as they ſay it is in throwing of a <hi>Granada,</hi> or fire-ball into a Caſtle, if you throw it <hi>too ſoone,</hi> before it is ready to breake, the Enemy within may preſently <hi>caſt</hi> it <hi>backe</hi> upon you, and deſtroy you; if you hold it <hi>too long,</hi> it may <hi>flye</hi> abroad in your hand and deſtroy your ſelfe ere you can put it off. There is a certaine <hi>nicke</hi> of time to be taken, which our God, who hath <hi>all times in his hand,</hi> did hide from them, that they knew it not, and ſo their <note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. v. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery was great upon them.</hi> For <hi>ſome</hi> of them did ariſe up and attempt <hi>too ſoone, others</hi> of them ſtayd too long, and ſo all were broken in peeces with, by, their <hi>owne fire-workes,</hi> according to that promiſe, <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 7. v. 16. <hi>Nec enim lex juſtior ulla eſt, quam necis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices arte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>His miſchiefe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne upon his owne head, and his violent dealing ſhall come downe upon his owne pate.</hi> Adde wee alſo, that very many of theſe <hi>new-old-enemies</hi> were <hi>Covenanters,</hi> or ſuch as had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>negative Oath,</hi> that is, never more to beare Armes againſt the Parliament. They were <hi>Benhadads,</hi> that had been kindly intreated, and ſent away with an oath, as he: for <note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 20.34</note> 
                     <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi> tooke a Covenant, or ſome kinde of negative oath: and by this meanes our credulity and their ingagements, had put into them a <hi>greater capacity</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> to deceive and deſtroy us. Beſides, with thoſe were joyned many a treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116550:20"/>
                     <hi>Doeg,</hi> you know hee was a kinde of <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 22. v. 9, 10, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Spy-profeſſour,</hi> that betrayed and deſtroyed the Prieſts of the Lord. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <note n="e" place="margin">2 Sam. 16. v. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Ziba,</hi> that belyed, betrayed, his owne <hi>Maſter,</hi> to get his <hi>ſequeſtration.</hi> Now if <note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 15. v. 7, 8, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Abſoloms</hi> pretence of a <hi>vow</hi> at <hi>Hebron,</hi> gave <hi>advantage</hi> to his treaſon, and drew with him many men, <hi>in their ſimplicity:</hi> if <hi>Benhadads</hi> taking that <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Oath,</hi> made him the more apt and able to conquer <hi>Iſrael;</hi> then what ſnares, what rages, what deaths, have we eſcaped, in being delivered from <hi>falſe</hi> and hypocriticall enemies! Let this Obſervation bee crowned with that acknowledgement, <note n="g" place="margin">Pſa. 118. v. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>They compaſſed me about like bees; they are quenched as the fire of thornes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>4</label> 4. Obſerve we, that our dangers were <hi>fundamentall</hi> and <hi>radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call;</hi> I mean, they came moſt and neareſt to our <hi>head</hi> and <hi>heart,</hi> to our moſt noble and vitall parts. The <hi>tooth-ake,</hi> I confeſſe, is a very ſmart and tormenting paine: but yet not accounted mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. The <hi>Gout</hi> is very painefull, and may prove dangerous: but yet being in the hand or foot, 'tis more ſafe than the <hi>ſtone</hi> and <hi>Collicke,</hi> which ſit cloſer and are more perillous. But yet a <hi>Malignant fever</hi> upon the <hi>ſpirits:</hi> a <hi>Peſtilence</hi> or a <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green,</hi> that aymes ſpeedily, immediately at the heart; theſe are accounted <hi>preſent death,</hi> and therefore a <hi>recovery</hi> from thoſe is more highly <hi>eſteemed.</hi> Now, theſe <hi>fits</hi> and diſtempers of our <hi>ſecond warre,</hi> have all, generally, ſtrucke at the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>vitalls.</hi> Formerly, the <hi>warre</hi> kept it ſelfe more <hi>abroad,</hi> in the Weſt, or North, or North-weſt parts of the kingdome, for the moſt: and thoſe parts were reckoned by ſome, but as the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour members</hi> of the body. But now, as if the Enemy had learnd of King <hi>Benhadad, Not to</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">1 Kings 22. ver. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>fight againſt ſmall nor great, in compariſon to the heart and head:</hi> As if they had learned of Biſhop <note n="b" place="margin">Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> 
                     <hi>Gardner,</hi> that one <hi>Salmons</hi> head was worth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Herrings;</hi> they have lately made all their <hi>blowes</hi> at our <hi>Parliament,</hi> and this great <hi>City.</hi> Our inſurrections, tumults, fightings, have been in <hi>Kent, Suſſex, Eſſex, Surry,</hi> yea in very <hi>Middleſex</hi> it ſelfe. Now, the <hi>whole head was ſicke, and the heart heavy indeed;</hi> the <hi>foundations were ſhaken:</hi> Our <hi>Corps-du-guard</hi> was aſſaulted, <hi>death</hi> came <hi>up into our windowes;</hi> when
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116550:20"/>our Parliament and City, the whole cauſe and party, have been ſayed downe at <hi>every ſtake,</hi> and have had ſo many, neere, and dangerous <hi>caſts</hi> throwne <hi>at them.</hi> Give me leave to deſcribe thoſe <hi>palpitations</hi> of <hi>Englands</hi> heart in a few borrowed words, <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 7. ver. 5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>We were troubled on every ſide; without were fightings, with in were feares, nevertheleſſe the Lord, who comforteth thoſe that are caſt downe, comforted us.</hi> Remember and forget not, how death did <hi>knocke</hi> at your very <hi>doore:</hi> what, Alarms and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, even at <hi>both ends</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Eaſt and Weſt? what, dangers, and talkings of <hi>ſurpriſing</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> where they were <hi>ſitting,</hi> of <hi>ſeiſing</hi> upon <hi>Lambeth-houſe,</hi> and planting guns upon it, to batter and annoy you in your very houſe whileſt you were ſitting? was the <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> nearer or more fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall than this? Take your pens (Honourable Senators) take your pens and <hi>write</hi> it down, firſt in your <hi>own Table books,</hi> and then in the <hi>Journall</hi> of your <hi>Houſe,</hi> and over the <hi>Chaire</hi> of your Speaker; <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 124. v. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>If it had not bin the Lord who was on our ſide, now may</hi> England <hi>ſay; if it had not bin the Lord, then they had ſwallowed us up quick whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wrath was kindled againſt us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="5"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>5</label> 5. Obſerve we, that thoſe dangers were <hi>new, freſh,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſive.</hi> This laſt warre hath been <hi>doubly</hi> new: new in reſpect of <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>new</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Scene</hi> and <hi>places</hi> in which it hath broken forth. For <hi>time,</hi> it is now come on, when the Land had began to <hi>reſt againe;</hi> and when we thought we had been neere the <hi>ſhoare,</hi> behold, an <hi>Euroclydon</hi> driveth us backe into the <hi>Ocean.</hi> But for its place and <hi>Scene,</hi> there is much to be obſerved. <hi>Thoſe parts</hi> of the Kingdome which had hitherto beene <hi>untoucht,</hi> the <hi>Mayden Counties,</hi> as they call them, have been now moſt of all <hi>defloured.</hi> Unconquered <hi>Kent,</hi> which had ſo long been famous for her almoſt <hi>veſtall</hi> virginity, hath had a principall ſhare of theſe troubles. And her ſiſter <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is now in the <hi>furnace.</hi> Beſides <hi>Surrey, Middleſex, Hertford, Huntington, Suffolke,</hi> and <hi>Norfolke;</hi> if they have not beene <hi>ſcorched</hi> by the flame, yet have they had ſome of the <hi>ſmoake</hi> in their eyes, whileſt their <hi>neighbours</hi> houſes have been on fire. For mine owne part, I dare not to <hi>determine,</hi> the <hi>cauſes</hi> of their freſh and new viſitation. I will not ſay, that the warre
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116550:21"/>marcht into thoſe <hi>freſh-quarters</hi> (1.) becauſe God will have his <note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 25. v. 15. 16. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>cup to goe round,</hi> when once hee begins to ſend it forth, though I read that hath been his uſuall method. Or (2.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>fire</hi> of warre and tumult had not ſo good <hi>fuell</hi> of plunder to feed it in other exhauſted Counties, as in theſe; nor ſo ready <hi>Fuellers</hi> to intertaine it; other people, like the <hi>burnt child,</hi> dreading the <hi>Coales.</hi> Neither (3.) will I ſay that it was, becauſe theſe people, like <hi>dandled</hi> children, did <hi>need a rod</hi> to teach them <hi>experimentall</hi> ſympathy and compaſſion. In ſumme, I will not dare, (as in Gods ſtead) to give the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſon or cauſe of this their new ſcourge. But yet it would become the <hi>ſuffering</hi> and warned people themſelves, to <hi>conſider</hi> of all poſſible conjectures; and to <hi>examine themſelves</hi> by all interrogatories that can be ſuggeſted, what may bee the provoking cauſe of this new <hi>ſtorm</hi> upon them. What, did I call it a <hi>ſtorm?</hi> Nay, rather it is yet but a little <hi>miſt,</hi> or as ſome <hi>few drops</hi> before a ſhowre, as that <note n="a" place="margin">1 King. 18. v. 44.</note> 
                     <hi>cloud like a mans hand.</hi> The Lord make the inhabitants of theſe yet <hi>unplundered</hi> Counties, Cities, Townes, Pariſhes, to bee <hi>wiſe for themſelves,</hi> that they may not cry for a rod, or grow ſick of their owne <hi>peace.</hi> But let them know and beleeve, that thoſe that drink <hi>laſt</hi> of the Cup, are neereſt the <hi>bottome,</hi> and the nearer the bottome, the more <hi>ſoure</hi> and <hi>deadly;</hi> for there lye the Lees and dregs, <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 75. v. 7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>The dregs thereof all the wicked of the earth ſhall wring them and drinke them out.</hi> O pray this cup from you.</p>
                  <p>But there was much <hi>mercy</hi> even in the midſt of this new, progreſſive <hi>miſery,</hi> in that the ſword <hi>went forward</hi> into freſh Quarters, and yet was <hi>ſtaid,</hi> wherby our deliverance appeareth the more wonderfull, in that the Lord did ſo ſoone <hi>quench</hi> the fire even amidſt a multitude of <hi>freſh fuell;</hi> yea amidſt ſo much ripe <hi>corne</hi> and dry <hi>ſtraw</hi> as was about it on every ſide. Surely, God did but only <hi>fire</hi> their <hi>Beacons</hi> hitherto rather than their <hi>houſes:</hi> they were <hi>Sentinels</hi> rather than <hi>Armies</hi> that were ſent amongſt them; even enough, I hope, to <hi>alarme,</hi> awaken, and inſtruct them, but not ſo many as to <hi>deſtroy</hi> and devoure them. <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 107. v. 43.</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſo is wiſe and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116550:21"/>
                  <p n="6"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>6</label> 6. Obſerve we, the evident <hi>unſproſperouſnes</hi> and viſible <hi>diſappointments</hi> of the Enemy, in all theſe dangers and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veratices. The whole conflict doth looke as if it had been a <hi>pitcht</hi> battell, a challenged <hi>Duell,</hi> or ſolemne <hi>prize</hi> playd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Michael</hi> and the Dragon, God and his enemies. Like as when the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Albanes</hi> did <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Miſſo in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium bello, ter gemenis hinc atque inde fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus utriuſque populi fata commiſſa ſunt.</hi> Flor.</note> 
                     <hi>Epitomize</hi> their warre, and tryed it in a combate between three Brethren, (the <hi>Curiatii</hi>) on the one ſide; and other three Brethren (the <hi>Horatii</hi>) on the other ſide: For never did the <hi>Enemy,</hi> on his part, act more numerouſly, ſubtilly, valiantly, by ſo many, ſo treacherous, ſo daring, attempts, as in this bout. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did the <hi>Lord</hi> appeare more plentifully, more profoundly, more peremptorily, for his poore people. And ſeeing it is both the <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>delight</hi> of a Saint, to tell others <hi>what the Lord hath done for</hi> his <hi>ſoule.</hi> Give me leave to reckon up <hi>ſome</hi> of the moſt viſible and mighty <hi>paſſes</hi> or <hi>thruſts,</hi> that have been made between the Lord and his enemies, in theſe late emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>encounters.</hi> We will reduce them to three or foure heads, which are as ſo many <hi>weapons,</hi> at which <hi>Michael</hi> and the Dragon have plaid this Prize.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Revolts.</note> 1. How hath the Enemy put to it againſt us, by <hi>revolts?</hi> This is a <hi>miſchievous</hi> weapon indeed, it coſt <note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 3. &amp; 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> his Cauſe, Crowne, and life, when <hi>Abner</hi> in diſcontent <hi>went over</hi> to <hi>David.</hi> And it hath ſeemed more <hi>ſuccesfull</hi> to the Enemy then all the reſt of his endeavours. But have their <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts</hi> always <hi>proſpered?</hi> Aske <hi>Pembroke</hi> caſtle, that great Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and neſt of the Revolters; Beſides <hi>Tenbigh</hi> caſtle in <hi>Wales.</hi> Aske thoſe Forces of the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> and thereabouts, that were <hi>apoſtatizing</hi> to <hi>Langdale,</hi> but come ſhort at <hi>Cocquet</hi> water, where 'twixt five and ſix hundred horſe were taken. And beleeve it, Our God is a righteous Lord <hi>(Tam in ſalo, quam in ſolo)</hi> aſwell upon the <hi>Seas</hi> as on the dry <hi>Land.</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 65.5.</note> 
                     <hi>By terrible things in righteouſneſſe wilt thou anſwer us, O God of our ſalvation, who art the confidence of all the ends of the earth, and of them that are afarre off upon the ſea.</hi> Therefore feare not <hi>Sea enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Surprizes.</note> 2. The Enemy hath tryed it at <hi>ſurpriſes</hi> too; This is alſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116550:22"/>a very <hi>dangerous</hi> weapon, as appeareth by the counſell of <hi>Achitophel</hi> the Oracle, <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 17. v. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>I will come upon him when he is weary and weak handed, and will make him afraid, and all the people that are with him ſhall flee, and I will ſmite the King onely.</hi> But hath not the Lord <hi>worſted</hi> them at this <hi>weapon</hi> alſo? Aske <hi>Denbigh</hi> caſtle in <hi>Wales,</hi> where the treacherous Enemy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined with a party of priſoners and ſouldiers within, had <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,</hi> was in part <hi>poſſeſt,</hi> and yet wonderfully diſcovered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed, vanquiſhed. Aske the <hi>Citie</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> where the <hi>day was</hi> come, the Enemy hovering and ready to enter, but diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> where the <hi>neck</hi> was neere the <hi>block,</hi> yet ſcaped the blow: of <hi>Norwich</hi> (formerly) where they <hi>ſtrucke,</hi> but the blow fell ſhort, nay <hi>fell back</hi> upon themſelves: of <hi>Nottingham caſtle,</hi> in which ſome of the <hi>ſurpriſers</hi> were <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed</hi> and impriſoned. Aske that conſpiracy in the Counties of <hi>Worceſter, Hereford</hi> and others adjacents there was a whole <hi>neſt</hi> full of <hi>eggs</hi> of treaſon, which were <hi>blowne upon</hi> and daſht ſo earely, that one could hardly tell what <hi>birds</hi> were in them, whether <hi>Owles</hi> or <hi>Eagles.</hi> Surely that <hi>diſcovery</hi> and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment deſerveth to have its <hi>Pillar</hi> of remembrance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected upon the banks of <hi>Severne,</hi> with the names of the active inſtruments engraven upon it. Nay aske finally, that their muſt <hi>ſuccesfull ſurpriſe</hi> of <hi>Pomfrect,</hi> hath it grown <hi>gray</hi> in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes? did not their <hi>foot</hi> alſo <hi>ſlide in due time</hi> at <hi>Willoughby field,</hi> where their <hi>ſpoyling Band</hi> was broken, taken, ſcattered? This muſt bee cloſed up with that of <hi>David,</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 21. v. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>They imagined a miſchievous device, which they were not able to performe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Inſurrections</note> 3. They have ſought with the deſperate weapon of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Inſurrections</hi> and Commotions. But were they Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours at this? I might here appeal to that Paire of <hi>Clergy,</hi> neer Stamford (but that one of them falling headlong, is burſt aſunder in the midſt) I mean that Jolly paire, that imitated <hi>Pope Iulius</hi> the ſecond, that caſt <hi>Peters Keyes</hi> into Tiber, and betooke himſelfe to <hi>Pauls ſword.</hi> I might aske, concerning them, how many houres that <hi>yong Commotion</hi> did ſmoake, and proſper? O moſt <hi>vigilant</hi> Commanders and <hi>Colonels,</hi> that ſcarcely ſlept in all the time of their command! <hi>Another</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116550:22"/>Inſurrection I muſt inſtance in. It was in the uttermoſt part of the utmoſt part of <hi>England weſtward,</hi> neere the <hi>Mount,</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> 'twas <hi>Dangerous</hi> I aſſure you, though ſuddenly and gallantly ſuppreſt and <hi>quenched</hi> in the <hi>Sea,</hi> forſome of the principall <hi>firebrands</hi> themſelves, were ſo deſperate, that ſcorning mercy, they joyned hand in hand and violently ran themſelves into the Ocean, where <hi>they periſhed in the waters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Battells.</note> 4. There was yet one terrible weapon more, at which our Enemies would needs fight it out with our God, and that was open, <hi>pitcht battels,</hi> and fixed <hi>Garriſons</hi> (to that ſtrength were they grown in ſome places) was not <hi>Willoughby field</hi> a ſet <hi>battell?</hi> were not <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Maydſtone, Garriſons?</hi> Beſides that <hi>Scene</hi> of the <hi>Barons warres,</hi> neere <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> and its <hi>cataſtrophe</hi> at <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Neots.</hi> Here the hot and hardy taking in of <hi>Maydſtone</hi> would not be left out, becauſe it was the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and <hi>Axeltree</hi> (in probability) of all thoſe after victories, and was <hi>one</hi> of the many <hi>lives</hi> which God had given to this Parliament. Thus every where, and in every attempt, may you write theſe new, ſecond, Enemies, <note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 22.30.</note> 
                     <hi>Conijah-like, child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> men that <hi>do not proſper in their dayes</hi> and wayes. But there are <hi>two branches</hi> out of this laſt root: I will gather the fruit of them, and I have done with it.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. To Enemies.</note> 1. A word to the <hi>Adverſe party.</hi> Sirs, will you not <hi>yet ſee</hi> the hand of God ſtretched out againſt you from heaven, in all this <hi>ſecond warre?</hi> Will you not ſee a <hi>ſword,</hi> like that in <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> way, <hi>meeting</hi> you at every turne? what? Croſt, diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, broken, in every plot, battell, attempt? <hi>Neither</hi> Revolts, nor Surprizes, nor Inſurrections, nor Commotions <hi>ſucceed</hi> with <hi>any</hi> of you, in <hi>any</hi> place, at <hi>any</hi> time? What? will you neither <hi>heare</hi> the Lords word, nor <hi>feel</hi> his worke? How often ſhall <hi>that text</hi> be <hi>beaten</hi> into pour fleſh, <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 54.17.</note> 
                     <hi>No wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that is formed againſt thee ſhall proſper, and every tongue that riſeth up in judgement, thou ſhalt condemne; This is the heritage of the ſervants of the Lord?</hi> O remember, how <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs ſervants</hi> did give him good counſell in <hi>time,</hi> if he would have hearkned, <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 10.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Knoweſt thou not yet that Egypt is deſtroyed?</hi> So I, to you; know yee not yet that Poore <hi>England,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116550:23"/>Mother of us all, is almoſt <hi>ruined?</hi> Nay, that many of your own <hi>companions,</hi> are already <hi>cut off?</hi> But you will <hi>deſpiſe</hi> that <hi>counſell?</hi> ſo did <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> till at laſt, himſelfe, and all his Militia, were forced to beleeve, confeſſe, and yet periſh in the <hi>bottome of the Sea.</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 14. v. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>And it came to paſſe that in the morning watch, the Lord looked unto the hoſt of the Egyptians, through the pillar of fire and of the cloud, and troubled the hoſt of the Egyptians.</hi> Hath not the Lord appeared for his ſervants, and againſt you, with open face, in the <hi>morning</hi> of this your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond war? Hath he not <hi>troubled</hi> all your hoſts, <hi>and taken off</hi> their Charret <hi>wheels</hi> that they drave them heavily? Surely, you muſt all ſubſcribe to this, that the Lord hath <hi>unwheeled</hi> all your late projects and attempts. The <hi>Egyptians ſaid, Let us flee from the face of Iſrael, for the Lord fighteth for them againſt the Egyptians.</hi> But then it was too late; they might confeſſe, to the honour of the Lords juſtice, but could not thereby help themſelves. The Lord give you all to ſee in the evening, in the <hi>Eleventh houre,</hi> of this your day, the things that concerne your peace.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2 To friends.</note> 2. Howſoever, be <hi>incouraged</hi> by this freſh and cleare expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, O all ye <hi>friends of God</hi> and his cauſe, and learne from theſe laſt and greateſt appearings of God for you, to ſee, and ſay, that <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 32. v. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>their rock is not as our rock, our enemies themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judges.</hi> I dare callenge them all, to name that <hi>one attempt,</hi> in which they have been ſuccesfull, in this their ſecond offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive war: Or if they have <hi>ſeemed</hi> at firſt to proſper in any thing, hath it not been only ſo far as might <hi>lift them up</hi> for the greater fall? But as for you, O friends, I charge all your hearts, to <hi>anſwer</hi> me ſeriouſly, did you ever ſee ſo much of God at once? Such a viſible hand from heaven, with his <hi>Banner,</hi> and <hi>Motto</hi> in it, like that of the firſt Chriſtian <note n="c" place="margin">Euſebius in vita Conſtant. Magn.</note> Emperours <hi>(in hoc vinces:)</hi> what <hi>ſhould</hi> the Lord doe more? How <hi>would</hi> you have him to <hi>expreſſe</hi> himſelfe more plainely, unleſſe by ſome audible <hi>voyce</hi> from heaven? Nay, but that is alſo vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed you, hearken to it; <note n="d" place="margin">2 Chron. 15. ver. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord is with you, whilſt ye are with him.</hi> It was one of Gods firſt ſolemne <hi>Meſſages</hi> to you in the beginning of your Faſtings, and hath been often incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116550:23"/>upon thoſe dayes. What God will doe <hi>with us</hi> at laſt, in this great cauſe, I know not: perhaps he may make us as great monuments of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the end, as he hath made us wonders of his <hi>Mercy</hi> in the beginning: (yet let me interline this <hi>comfort,</hi> he doth not uſe to caſt off a <hi>coming-people;</hi>) but if we ſhould <hi>periſh</hi> in the concluſion, yet we muſt ſay and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that <hi>hitherto</hi> he hath been, and <hi>yet</hi> he is, <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 28. v. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>wonderfull in counſell, excellent in working for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> But <hi>how</hi> can that be, ſeeing we were never ſo <hi>unworthy,</hi> unwilling, unfit for <hi>mercy,</hi> as at this time? never ſo profane, divided, bitter, againſt God and one another?</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> All this is <hi>confeſſed,</hi> and a great deal <hi>more,</hi> if any wil ad it: but therefore know, that we muſt not <hi>thanke</hi> our ſelves, but our <hi>enemies,</hi> for theſe ſucceſſes; not our owne goodneſſe, but their wickedneſſe is the cauſe of all our late victories. Though we are not ripe for <hi>Mercy,</hi> yet they are ripe for <hi>judgment,</hi> though God be not more ingaged <hi>for us</hi> then formerly, yet (ſure I am,) he is more ingaged <hi>againſt them.</hi> He was before ingaged againſt them as he was <note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 10. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>King of Nations,</hi> and they fought for <hi>tyranny</hi> againſt our juſt and lawfull liberties. But now as <note n="c" place="margin">Rev. 15. v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>the King of Saints,</hi> he will fight againſt them for treacherie, hypocriſie, and forſworne Covenant-breaking. In ſhort, the Lord is now <hi>many wayes</hi> ingaged againſt them. (1.) As enemies againſt <hi>Reformation</hi> and civill <hi>liberties.</hi> (2.) As <hi>ungratefull</hi> to thoſe that have <hi>ſpared</hi> them. (3.) As <hi>deceitfull</hi> and treacherous againſt Oathes, Articles, and Covenants. (4.) As bitter <hi>Formaliſts</hi> againſt the power of godlineſſe. There is a <hi>comfortable</hi> Text, in this particular, in the book of <hi>Iob;</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Job 17. ver. 18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>The innocent ſhall ſtirre up himſelfe againſt the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, the righteous alſo ſhall hold on his way, and hee that hath cleane hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger.</hi> Marke the words, Doth the Lord <hi>command</hi> or promiſe, that the <hi>innocent</hi> ſhall ſtir up himſelfe againſt the hypocrite? And will not <hi>God</hi> ſtirre up <hi>himſelfe</hi> againſt them? Yea, beleeve it, he is more ingaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an <hi>hypocrite,</hi> then againſt the open <hi>profane</hi> perſon. (1.) Becauſe ſuch an one is <hi>profane,</hi> and ſomewhat <hi>more,</hi> he is as wicked <hi>within</hi> as the other, and yet <hi>pretends</hi> to godlineſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116550:24"/>
                     <hi>without.</hi> (2.) Becauſe he doth <hi>cauſe the way of God to be evill ſpoken of,</hi> which is a pitch of wickedneſſe, of which the open profane perſon is <hi>uncapable:</hi> therefore the Lord doth, will, muſt ſtirre up himſelfe againſt him above <hi>all others.</hi> He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>And the righteous ſhall hold on his way,</hi> that is, both his way of piety, and of proſperity, but the hypocrite muſt needs hobble, lame, and tire, both in his holineſſe and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for both are as a <note n="a" place="margin">Hoſ. 6 ver. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>morning cloud and an early dew that paſſeth away.</hi> Once more, <hi>he that hath cleane hands ſhall bee ſtronger and ſtronger;</hi> then what ſhall become of him that hath <hi>foule hands,</hi> whether by fleſh, earth, or bloud? Surely, he muſt needs grow <hi>weaker</hi> and <hi>weaker.</hi> Feare not therefore the faces of ſuch men (Honourable Senators) feare them not. He hath ſaid it, and you may <hi>adventure</hi> your lives upon it. Were I to <hi>chooſe</hi> mine owne <hi>enemy,</hi> I would, above all other, chooſe to fight againſt an <hi>ungratefull hypocrite,</hi> becauſe both God, and all reaſonable men, muſt needs abhor him. It is a famous example and ſentence that we finde recorded in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiell. Zedekiah</hi> the King of Judah had his <hi>condition,</hi> changed, from a private man to a Prince, and with it, his <hi>name</hi> changed from <hi>Mattaniah</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah.</hi> Hereupon he ſweareth <hi>fidelity</hi> to that King of Babylon which ſo advanced him; but upon advantage, baſely <hi>brake his Oath and faith</hi> with him, betaking himſelfe to the King of Egypt for aſſiſtance. For this, <hi>God</hi> fals upon him, takes the Babylonians part againſt him, and puts theſe interrogatories. <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 17. v. 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>[Shall be proſper? ſhall he eſcape that doth ſuch things? Or ſhall he breake the Covenant and be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered? As I live, ſaith the Lord God, in the place where the King dwelleth that made him King, whoſe Oath he deſpiſed, and whoſe Covenant he brake, even with him, in the midſt of Babylon, he ſhall die, neither ſhall</hi> Pharaoh <hi>with his mighty Army, and great company, make for him in the warre, by caſting up mounts and building forts, to cut off many perſons, ſith he deſpiſed the Oath, by breaking the Covenant (when lo, he had given his hand) and hath done all theſe things; he ſhall not eſcape.</hi> Reade tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the following verſes, to the end of that Chapter, we doe all know, how truly and ſadly this was <hi>fulfilled</hi> upon him, for it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116550:24"/>is at leaſt <hi>twice thus recorded</hi> in Scripture. Jeruſalem, <note place="margin">2 Kings 25. v. 4.5, 6, 7. Jer. 52. v. 6, 7.</note> that whole Kingdome was loſt; <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Zedekiah</hi> taken, his ſons ſlaine before his eyes, then his eyes put out, himſelfe bound with fetters of braſſe, and carried to Babylon, where he dyed.</q> Nay, one example more. The Lord will take the <hi>part,</hi> even of a <hi>Turke,</hi> againſt a <hi>perfidious Chriſtian.</hi> To this purpoſe, <hi>remember</hi> and forget not, ſo long as you have to doe with this kinde of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, (the treacherous and perfideous Covenant-breaker) <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not</hi> the famous battell of <hi>Varna.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The battell of <hi>Varna:</hi> See Turkiſh Hiſt. in <hi>Amurath</hi> ſixth King of the Turks. pag. 287.</note> It was fought betweene <hi>Amurath</hi> ſixth King of the Turks, and <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Hungary.</hi> Theſe two after much war between them, at laſt concluded a <hi>peace</hi> for tenne yeares, confirmed it ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, by taking their mutuall <hi>Oathes:</hi> the Chriſtian upon the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> the Turke upon his <hi>Alcharon.</hi> This done, <hi>Amurath</hi> ſecurely <hi>withdrawes</hi> his Forces out of <hi>Europe,</hi> and leaveth his Countries there ungarded. Upon this <hi>advantage,</hi> and ſome others, King <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> by the <hi>perſwaſions</hi> of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Cardinall, diverſe Chriſtian Princes, and many Prelates (pretending that it would bee for the good of Religion and the Chriſtian cauſe) is induced to <hi>breake</hi> the <hi>peace</hi> and his <hi>Oath</hi> (of which <hi>Iulian</hi> abſolveth him) hee taketh up armes and <hi>invadeth</hi> the Turks dominions: where at <hi>firſt</hi> he ſeems to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper,</hi> and carry all before him; till at laſt his Army meetes the Turkes (who by this, had made head againſt him) in the <hi>pitched</hi> battell of <hi>Varna:</hi> where the victory, almoſt all the day, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth to the Chriſtians, inſomuch as <hi>Amurath</hi> himſelfe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to <hi>flee,</hi> till a common Souldier laid hand upon his bridle, and ſtayed him. The fight is again <hi>renewed,</hi> and the Chriſtians againe have the <hi>better;</hi> till <hi>Amurath</hi> now almoſt deſpairing, eſpied the picture of the Crucifix in the diſplayed <hi>Enſignes</hi> of the Chriſtians, and then, plucking out the <hi>writing</hi> that contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their laſt League and peace, out of his boſome, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it up in his hand, with his eyes caſt up to heaven, he ſaid; <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Behold,</hi> thou crucified Chriſt, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                        </label> this is the League the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in thy Name, made with me, which they have, without any cauſe, violated. Now if thou be a God, as they ſay thou art, and as we dreame, revenge the wrong now done
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116550:25"/>unto thy Name and me, and ſhew thy power upon thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious people, who in their deeds deny thee their God.</q> Immediately the <hi>battell</hi> began to <hi>turne</hi> for the Turks againſt the Chriſtians, and that, firſt of all, in that part where <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> did command: And without delay the Turkes breake all the Chriſtians forces <hi>in peeces;</hi> King <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> is <hi>ſlaine</hi> upon the place, <hi>Iulian,</hi> mortally wounded, <hi>dyes</hi> in his flight; beſides divers great <hi>Prelates</hi> and Commanders, with many thouſands of common men. Remember it again; God will <hi>take part</hi> with an <hi>Amurath,</hi> with an appealing <hi>Turk;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a perfidious <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> though a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Let us <hi>keep</hi> our Covenant in our <hi>boſome,</hi> and remember to ſhew and pleade it in like time and caſe. This was the ſixth Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="7"> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>7</label> 7. And now to this <hi>halfe dozen</hi> of obſervable mercies, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Lord hath given you in a kind of <hi>caſt-over;</hi> a <hi>ſeventh</hi> obſervable, which I muſt call, a <hi>meeting-mercy:</hi> For I beleeve you ſhall finde, that the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Pembrooke</hi> Caſtle, and your <hi>Order</hi> for this Thankſgiving, doe both beare the ſame date and day, even the <hi>twelfth</hi> of this inſtant. The Pſalmiſt ſaith of his <hi>prayers,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. v. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>I ſaid I will confeſſe my tranſgreſſions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſinne.</hi> So was it in your <hi>praiſes,</hi> you <hi>ſaid</hi> that you would give thankes unto the Lord for his mercies received, and he gave you <hi>another</hi> great favour the ſame day. Let it be called a <hi>meeting-mercy,</hi> for that reaſon: As alſo becauſe the Spirit of God ſeemes to give it that very <hi>name</hi> in the Scripture; <note place="margin">Iſa. 64. ver. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou [meeteſt] him that rejoyceth and worketh righteouſneſſe, thoſe that remember thee in thy wayes.</hi> You were <hi>about</hi> to rejoyce in the Lord, and to remember his way of mercy, and, behold, he <hi>met</hi> you in your rejoycing. One ſuch a <hi>meeting-mercy,</hi> ſuch an <hi>after-caſt</hi> of meer favour, is to be eſteemed as much as a whole <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi> It is like <hi>fruit</hi> upon a <hi>graffe,</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> yeare of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing: For your <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> did <hi>beare</hi> the ſame day that it was <hi>ſet.</hi> Let it therefore be your care and endeavour to <hi>meet</hi> the Lord often in this way, that you may as often be <hi>met</hi> by him.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116550:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">3 Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</note> The laſt leſſon muſt be a ſhort, but ſtrong <hi>incouragement.</hi> Now will you? can you? dare you to diſtruſt the Lord <hi>another time?</hi> will you warpe and waver from, or in, his way againe <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after?</hi> I give you leave to do it, if you can finde a <hi>better</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if you can meet with any <hi>other</hi> God that <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note> 
                     <hi>can deliver</hi> you <hi>after this ſort.</hi> But if there be <hi>none</hi> ſuch to be found, then <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> 
                     <hi>take heed, leſt there be in any of you hereafter, an evill heart of unbeliefe, in departing from this living God.</hi> Let the <hi>heads</hi> of theſe <hi>Leviathans</hi> be as <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 74.14.</note> 
                     <hi>meat to you in the wilderneſſe;</hi> For I beleeve we have a <hi>long</hi> way of wilderneſſe yet <hi>to goe;</hi> but <hi>feed</hi> upon theſe paſt <hi>experiences,</hi> in all your new and future <hi>Marches.</hi> Let this <hi>double breakfaſt</hi> ſtrengthen and inable you ( <note n="d" place="margin">1 King. 19.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Elijah-like</hi>) for the great journeys which you have yet to go. Perhaps they are not of <hi>forty dayes</hi> onely, (as was his) but for many <hi>more</hi> weekes or moneths; when you are to travell through <hi>briers and thornes,</hi> before your worke, or your ſelves, may arrive at the <hi>mount of God:</hi> Wherefore <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>gird up the loynes of your [mind:]</hi> All ſaints have or ſhould have but <hi>one</hi> minde, or <hi>heart. Be ſober and hope unto the end,</hi> or truſt perfectly: It is a <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>word</hi> that I cannot mention without a <hi>note</hi> upon it; Truſt God <hi>to the end;</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>meanes,</hi> as <note n="g" place="margin">1 Kings 17.12.15.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhee</hi> that at Gods command gave a <hi>Cake</hi> out of her <hi>laſt</hi> handfull and little oyle: and was ſhe a loſer by it? As thoſe <hi>three worthies</hi> at <hi>Babylon,</hi> when they ſaid, <note n="h" place="margin">Dan. 3.16, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Our God whom wee ſerve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace:</hi> but the hard queſtion was, whether he <hi>would</hi> doe it? Yes, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the <hi>evill,</hi> or from the <hi>extremity</hi> of the <hi>evill,</hi> they beleeve; <hi>Hee will deliver us out of [thy hand] O King, i. e.</hi> He will ſo preſerve us, that thou ſhalt not have thy will upon us. But how were they <hi>ſure</hi> of that? What if he ſhould not have vouchſafed <hi>that</hi> unto them neither? <hi>But if not be it knowne unto thee O KING, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> As he <note n="a" place="margin">Nil niſi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum metuo.</note> replyed to that Meſſenger I feare nothing but ſinne.</p>
                  <p>So much for the <hi>former halfe</hi> of the <hi>text,</hi> concerning the <hi>praiſe of thanksgiving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116550:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2 Part of the text.</note> I want time and ſpirits to ſpeake to the <hi>latter part</hi> as I would, concerning <hi>[Ordering the way aright.]</hi> This clauſe ſtandeth here in the <hi>middeſt,</hi> between the God-glorifying du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>praiſe,</hi> and the men-bleſſing mercy of <hi>ſalvation;</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>top-ſtone</hi> of praiſes, and the <hi>corner-ſtone</hi> of deliverance; <hi>To him that ordereth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</hi> Whence wee might fetch a double Leſſon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That <hi>a right ordering of the way, is the perfection of Thanksgiving.</hi> And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That <hi>it is the beſt ſtep to a compleat ſalvation.</hi> But to put both into one, Thus.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Right Ordering of the way is the top-ſtone of all duty,</hi> and <hi>the corner-ſtone of all deliverance.</hi> We have heard, that <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> is the <hi>crowne</hi> of <hi>duty;</hi> now <hi>Right ordering</hi> the <hi>way,</hi> or converſation, is the <hi>pearle</hi> of that crowne, and the very <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of that <hi>honour.</hi> It is ſomewhat to <hi>praiſe</hi> with the <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 63.34.</note> 
                     <hi>mouth,</hi> by ſpeaking praiſes; It is more to praiſe with the <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 77.11 12.</note> 
                     <hi>heart</hi> by meditating Thankſgivings: but it is moſt of all to praiſe in the <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 1.12, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Application.</note> 
                     <hi>life,</hi> by ordering the converſation aright, <hi>that we ſhould [bee] to the praiſe of his glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Applica.</hi> Would you then <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord <hi>indeed?</hi> Would you <hi>certainely and fully ſee</hi> the ſalvation of God? Then for the <hi>Lords ſake,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Si enim male vivis, &amp; bona dicis, nondum laudas. Non ergo lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, qui malè viuendo offendit Dominum.</hi> Auſt. <hi>ad</hi> Pſal. 49.</note> as you would honour him; for your <hi>owne ſake,</hi> as you would ſave your ſelves and the kingdome; doe but <hi>order the way aright,</hi> and then I dare promiſe you that he ſhall be <hi>glorified</hi> by you, and <hi>yee</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſaved</hi> by him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt. Order the way aright?</hi> What is that?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let it be <hi>what</hi> it <hi>will,</hi> what it <hi>can,</hi> though never ſo <hi>coſtly,</hi> never ſo <hi>painefull,</hi> never ſo <hi>hazardous,</hi> it is worth all the charge, labour and perill, that you can undergo. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>reſolve</hi> upon it it at all adventures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what is it then?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Take it in ſhort; <hi>[Right ordering]</hi> doth <hi>containe</hi> theſe <hi>two things,</hi> as I finde in Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A right <hi>ſetting,</hi> methodizing, framing, or <hi>caſting</hi> of things into their proper <hi>order,</hi> ſhape and platforme. A put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of things into <hi>due place,</hi> and ſo it is applyed to the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116550:26"/>of <hi>battels.</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">1 King. 20.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſhall order [Heb.</hi> binde, or tye,] <hi>the battell? Hee anſwered, Thou.</hi> It is applyed to the ordering of a <hi>cauſe.</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 23 4. Iob 34.18.</note> 
                     <hi>I would order my cauſe before him, and fill my mouth with arguments.</hi> It is applyed to the ordering of the <hi>things of God.</hi> Thus <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes are appointed to <hi>order the</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Exo. 27.21.</note> 
                     <hi>lampe,</hi> and to <hi>order the</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Levit. 24.3.</note> 
                     <hi>burnt offering.</hi> Thus <note n="e" place="margin">Lev. 1.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Magiſtrate, is commanded to <hi>ſet in order the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi> with his appurtenances, and doth it. Thus <hi>David,</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">1. Chron. 24.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Hezekiah, Ezra, Nehemiah, ordered</hi> ſeverall affaires abut the houſe of the Lord; tis a <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 9.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio, correctio;</hi> Reformation <hi>Angl.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>right-ſetting.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It doth containe an <hi>eſtabliſhing,</hi> fixing, or ſetling of things in that right frame and order. As, <note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 4 26.</note> 
                     <hi>Ponder the pathes of thy feet, and let all thy wayes be eſtabliſhed,</hi> or, <hi>all thy wayes ſhall bee ordered aright.</hi> And elſewhere, theſe two are put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <note n="i" place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Beholding your order and ſtedfaſtneſſe.</hi> And thus, a right ordering, is not onely a putting of things into a <hi>right frame,</hi> but a <hi>fixing</hi> of them there: a <hi>right ſetting</hi> and a <hi>ſure ſettling.</hi> Would you but doe <hi>this,</hi> or doe your uttermoſt <hi>towards</hi> this, and then you might be ſaid to <hi>order the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> The way? What way?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are <hi>many</hi> neceſſary <hi>Cauſe wayes</hi> now to be ſet and ſettled, for want of which we wander and plunge our ſelves every where. Take ſome ſhort <hi>hints.</hi> The <hi>wayes</hi> that you are to <hi>order,</hi> are of two ſorts.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. <hi>Particular</hi> and <hi>perſonall</hi> wayes to be ordered aright.</note> I. More <hi>particularly,</hi> reſpecting <hi>your ſelves.</hi> And here again are two branches. </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Labour to order the wayes of <hi>your perſons and families</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: elſe you are like to doe <hi>little good</hi> or ſervice towards the <hi>publike.</hi> The Heathen could ſay, none but a <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nemo civis bonus, niſi vir bonus.</hi> Cicer.</note> 
                     <hi>good man</hi> could make a <hi>good Citizen.</hi> Remember <hi>Iacobs method,</hi> when he was whipt home to pay his vow, in building the Lord an Houſe at <hi>Bethel:</hi> he firſt falleth to purging his owne houſe. <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 34. ver. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>And God ſaid unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>Ariſe, and goe up to Bethel, and dwell there, and make there an Altar unto God, that appeared unto thee, when thou fleddeſt from the face of</hi> Eſau <hi>thy brother.</hi> Marke how he begins; <hi>Then</hi> Jacob <hi>ſaid unto his houſhold, and all that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116550:27"/>were with him, Put away the ſtrange gods that are amongſt you, and be cleane, and change your garments, and let us ariſe and goe up to</hi> Bethel, <hi>&amp;c. And they gave unto</hi> Jacob <hi>all the ſtrange gods which were in their hand, and all their earrings which were in their eares, and</hi> Jacob <hi>hid them under the Oke which was by Sichem.</hi> Remember <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>danger,</hi> for neglecting this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; when hee was to <hi>bring</hi> Iſrael out of the <hi>houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> he muſt have no <hi>uncircumciſed</hi> thing remaine in his owne houſe: <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 4. v. 24, 25, 26.</note> 
                     <hi>And it came to paſſe by the way in the Inne, the Lord met him, and ſought to kill him; then</hi> Zipporah <hi>tooke a ſharp ſtone, and cut off the foreskin of her ſonne, and caſt it at his feet, ſo he let him goe.</hi> I know the words are read by ſome in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, but you may ſafely and profitably gather that leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from them, <hi>To begin Reformation at home.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Order your <hi>owne way</hi> aright in <hi>reference</hi> to the publike. I meane, labour to walke and act, not by <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>An paſſim ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queris corvos, teſt â<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> luto<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſecurus quo pes ferat? at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ex tempore vivis?</hi> Perſ.</note> 
                     <hi>ſucceſſes</hi> and parties, but by <hi>rules</hi> and principles. How many publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments among us are like <hi>veſſells</hi> upon the <hi>Thames,</hi> that do riſe and fall, goe out and in, according to the ebbings and flowings of the River? O this hath been our great ſinne and miſery! Men have been generally like a <hi>herd of cattle</hi> in a ſhip at <hi>Sea,</hi> when the ſtorme doth roll the ſhip to <hi>this ſide,</hi> the brutiſh herd run all over to the other ſide, thinking thereby to avoyde the toſſe; but their weight ſoone <hi>brings backe</hi> the Veſſell, and then they <hi>flee over</hi> to the old ſide again, and ſo the ſhip is <hi>overſet,</hi> and all are drowned at laſt. Let us <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> our <hi>ground:</hi> keep cloſe to our ſtations; and ſtand <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> in our places. A man in a <hi>skirmiſh,</hi> gets a bullet as ſoone by <hi>ſtooping,</hi> as by ſtanding upright: yea, and perhaps by his crouching, that bullet takes him in the <hi>head,</hi> which elſe would have hit him but in the <hi>arme</hi> or <hi>ſhoulder.</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 10. v. 9. &amp; 28. v. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that walketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, walketh ſurely, and the Lord will be his</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 2. v. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>buckler.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Publike and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall wayes.</note> II. Concerning right ordering the <hi>publike wayes;</hi> they are divers. But let me tell you, ye have <hi>caſt</hi> your way, and your worke <hi>generally,</hi> very well, and rightly already, ye have your frames and <hi>Platforms</hi> well drawn forth, (1.) In our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and <hi>Covenant;</hi> an holy, juſt, and good Covenant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116550:27"/>it is in it ſelfe, and ſo we <hi>took</hi> it; how ever wicked men doe turne every ſtone to abaſe it. Beleeve it, that Covenant ſhall <hi>breake</hi> thoſe that deſigne to <hi>breake it;</hi> and if any ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make it as an old <hi>Almanacke,</hi> they will finde it full of <hi>red letters</hi> to them. Let us therefore ſhew our ſelves <hi>reall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters</hi> without racking or lopping. (2.) The conſtant <hi>tenour</hi> of your Declarations. Oh, would you but frequently <hi>reade</hi> them over! you know to whom it was ſaid; <hi>I beſeech Your Majeſty to reade over your booke.</hi> May it pleaſe you, to get all thoſe your ſolemne <hi>promiſes</hi> and Declarations, to God and man, at leaſt the principall of them, ſuch as that of <hi>both Kingdoms, &amp;c.</hi> to be <hi>bound up together</hi> in one book, and make that book, your <hi>Vade mecum,</hi> your pocket companion, where ever you go. Surely, this might be one effectuall meanes to order the way aright.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Neceſſary High-wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> of</note> To binde up all. There are <hi>foure</hi> publike <hi>high-wayes</hi> that ſhould be ordered aright.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Religion.</note> 1. The <hi>way of Religion.</hi> Till you ſet, and ſettle that, neither God, nor good men, will be your <hi>thorow friends.</hi> Let that <hi>Arke</hi> no longer dwell in <hi>Tents,</hi> without dores; neither let it be lodged within dores, in the <hi>bed</hi> of <hi>Procrustes.</hi> The <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-book</hi> it ſelfe was firſt intended for <hi>Crutches:</hi> they ruined themſelves, and it, that at laſt, made it a paire of <hi>Stoopes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Juſtice.</note> 2. The <hi>way of juſtice</hi> to <hi>Delinquents.</hi> Set and ſettle that, ſo far at leaſt, as to ſtop the mouthes of that party, which ſay, yee <hi>cannot try</hi> them, becauſe yee <hi>doe not.</hi> There is alſo a way of juſtice to your <hi>friends,</hi> that are ſunke for the cauſe of God, upon your command, and promiſe of ſupport.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Militia.</note> 3. The <hi>way of Defence.</hi> Set and ſettle that, for the for the <hi>ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> of the throats of all the godly and well affected through the Land, leſt the Enemy regaine all his loſt battels by one nights <hi>maſſacre,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> loſt all his victories in one houre, in the Senate houſe, and our <note n="*" place="margin">At, or neere <hi>Stonehenge</hi> in <hi>Wiltz.</hi>
                     </note> Britiſh <hi>Anceſtours</hi> loſt all by the Saxons skeynes or knives, which they had long kept and gotten from them by their <hi>ſwords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Mercy.</note> 4. The <hi>way of Mercy.</hi> Set and ſettle that, for your poore, helpleſſe, undone <hi>friends,</hi> whether undone in eſtates, bodies
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116550:28"/>or friends. Be mercifull to the poore <hi>broken families,</hi> and owners of families, of which there are ſo very many now in the Land, that have ſpent the laſt handfull of <hi>meale in the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,</hi> and <hi>oyle in the Cruſe,</hi> at Gods command and yours, in that publike cauſe. We <hi>Miniſters</hi> were inſtrumentall in putting them onwards upon thoſe disburſements, I pray give us now leave, to ſpeake a word, though not for their preſent <hi>repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> yet for preſent <hi>ſubſiſtence.</hi> Be mercifull to poore <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken bones:</hi> There are many ſuch <hi>pieces</hi> of maimed men, men walking like <hi>trees</hi> abroad in the <hi>Land,</hi> that want <hi>neceſſary</hi> food to ſuſtaine thoſe remainders of their bodies that are left, though here about the City, bleſſed be God, and bleſſed be your care, they are generally provided for. Be mercifull to poore <hi>broken,</hi> beheaded, and (as I may ſay) unbowelled <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies;</hi> Oh, how many, many, <hi>Widowes</hi> and <hi>Orphans</hi> are there, which know not whoſe to call themſelves, but <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>yours?</hi> The husband is dead, the father is ſlaine in the Kingdomes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the poore uncovered family hath <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 72. v. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>no helper.</hi> Yea, and many of theſe, which have moſt <hi>need,</hi> are the moſt <hi>ſilent:</hi> For the Lords ſake, let your <hi>bowels</hi> within you roll towards them. Think of ſome way to <note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeeke them out very diligently, till you finde them. And the Lord grant unto you, that you may find mercy of the Lord in that day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have but a few words more to adde. Make it your buſines (Honourable Senators) to <hi>follow God fully</hi> in this great <hi>Cauſe,</hi> at this needfull <hi>time,</hi> and remember that the <hi>veſſell</hi> which you doe ſteer, doth carry in her more then the eſtates, liberties, lives of three Kingdomes. For the eyes and expectations of all the <hi>Chriſtian world</hi> are towards you, the Proteſtants ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the Papiſts fearing your ſucceſſe; all the precious godly <hi>honeſt party</hi> in this and the other two Nations have adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their whole eſtates, lives, poſterities upon you; yea, their Religion and Reformation with you. With you muſt we and ours ſwim or ſink. Tis not now in your power to leave us where you found us, or to land us where we did imbarque; No, no, we muſt thorow, or ſinke in the middeſt; be better or worſe then ever. Ye are ſet up for the finall <hi>fall,</hi> or totall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116550:28"/>
                     <hi>riſing</hi> of godlineſſe, property, liberties in <hi>England;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your cloſure, ſo ſhall wee ſay, welcome, or fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, for ever, to happy or unhappy Parliaments in this Land. If you by Gods bleſſing ſhall faithfully and couragiouſly <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> us <hi>thorough</hi> this ſtorme and voyage, (which I <hi>doubt not</hi> if ye ſtand faſt to God and your friends) how ſhall all the Saints on earth, all the Angels in Heaven, and all the children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne bleſſe your perſons and memories? but if thorough wickedneſſe or weakneſſe, you, or any amongſt you ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray or deſtroy this glorious cauſe, (which God forbid) ſurely it had been better for you and us, that we had <hi>never beene borne:</hi> the ſinne, the ſcandall, the ruine, would bee unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, unanſwerable, intolerable. The name of <hi>Religion</hi> would be abhord in <hi>England;</hi> and the name of <hi>Engliſh</hi> hiſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at over all the world. There are many grounds of hopes and encouragement for you; remember the good old fervent <hi>prayers and martyrdomes</hi> which our godly <hi>Anceſtors</hi> have layd in for this time, ever ſince the dawning of our Reformation: Conſider the volleys of <hi>cryes,</hi> the bottles, rivers, of <hi>teares</hi> that have been powred out for you and your cauſe by all the Saints on earth ſince your ſitting, remember the <hi>wonders</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that your eyes have ſeen. You may, you may, you ſhall, ſave your ſelves, and us, and all, if you will. Oh, why <hi>will ye dye?</hi> Then <hi>ſtand faſt</hi> in the name of the Lord, to the great <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and to that holy and honeſt party, that have caſt their lives, eſtates, poſterities upon you; they are a <hi>precious</hi> though deſpiſed people, if you ſave them, you ſave your ſelves, if any of you ſhould forſake them, (eſpecially now that the <hi>ſhip</hi> is <hi>neere</hi> to a wrack, or an Anchor) ſuch <hi>apoſtats</hi> may thereby ruine themſelves, but yet that poore deare faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remnant have a God, who hath promiſed by a preſident that <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 27. v. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>When Father and Mother</hi> (King and Parliament) <hi>doe forſake;</hi> himſelfe <hi>will take them up.</hi> And therefore let all <hi>complementall</hi> formall <hi>Orpahs</hi> kiſſe, weep, and part, with that good old <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>party,</hi> as they will, when it ſhall from a <hi>Naomi</hi> (pleaſant) be turned by miſery, to a <hi>Marah</hi> (bitter:) yet muſt every one of us ſtill doe, and ſay, unto it, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116550:29"/>
                     <hi>Naomi,</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Ruth 1. v. 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Intreate me not to leave thee or to returne from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thee, after thee; for whither thou goeſt, I will goe, and where thou lodgeſt I will lodge, thy people ſhall be my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and thy God: my God and</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 13. v. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>when I am dead bury me</hi> (O my friends) <hi>in the Sepulcher wherein it is buried.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cum mihi ſupremos Lacheſis perneverit annos,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non alitèr cineres mando jacere meos.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116550:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Col</hi> 50 <hi>of</hi> 100. <hi>for a Cap: the Life guard is kept whole. The new Swediſh</hi> Generaliſſimo Charles Guſtave <hi>Palſgrave, is arived in</hi> Germany <hi>with</hi> 8000 <hi>men, he is to meet Maior</hi> Gen. Erlach, <hi>they have a deſigne againſt</hi> Collin, <hi>becauſe</hi> Lamboy <hi>hath alwayes his recruit from thence who hath an Armie again together, and endeavoureth to be revenged upon the Heſhiſh. Out of</hi> Weſtphalia <hi>is come unto him Count</hi> Hennigo, <hi>with</hi> 8 <hi>peeces of Ordnance, and</hi> 1400 <hi>foot: The Heſhiſh are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched neer</hi> Neuſe, <hi>expecting</hi> Lamboys comming, <hi>who hath about</hi> 3000 <hi>horſe, and as many foot. The Heſhiſh expect</hi> Landgrave Fredrick <hi>with his horſe, which if he doth not come timely, the other may be the hard for them. The Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>was to goe to</hi> Cleve <hi>to the chriſtning of his brother Prince Elector of</hi> Brandenburgs <hi>childe, but the day being put off to the</hi> 2 <hi>of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>is returned to the</hi> Hague, <hi>where the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour</hi> Pegneranda <hi>is expected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Engliſhſhips are ſaid to be riggd, but by whoſe leave, or by whom, is not known: not by any authority. At</hi> Oſnabrugk, <hi>the Ambaſſadour of</hi> Bavaria, <hi>having propounded that in caſe a peace ſhould not be ſuddenly concluded on, that his Maſter would take a courſe to preſerve Him and his Dominions; which being exploded by the Catholike Imperiall States,</hi> Bavaria <hi>thereupon reſolved to ſtand to the Emperor to the laſt. The</hi> Portugal <hi>Embaſſador at the</hi> Hague <hi>hath deſired the States (that ſeeing they had made an end of their great affairs with</hi> Spain) <hi>to begin to treat with him about the affairs of</hi> Fernambuck, <hi>that that Treaty being brought to a period, each party might enioy their own to the great benefit of both. Prince</hi> Charles <hi>of</hi> Wales <hi>hath been as</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, <hi>and is by this time in</hi> Holland, <hi>where he was expected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>Poland</hi> they have in nomination for King, the late Kings ſon by his former wife, Prince <hi>Caſſimire,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde:</hi> the revolted Parliament ſhips intend ſuddenly to be in the Downs, and to put in for a perſonall Treaty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Iuly</hi> 6.</label> The Commons permitted Major Gen: <hi>Brovvne</hi> to be Shrieve of <hi>London,</hi> approved of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Counties geting into armes for defence before authority came to them, Letters from their Commiſſioners out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of there proceeding being approved were ordered to be printed, as for their comming back to <hi>England</hi> they did not think it fit as yet, they being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Miniſters, and while peace is between the Nations, it was thought fit they continue to be ready to give and receive what was given or received.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>The</hi> 7.</label> Letter came from the Noble Army inviting the City to a concurrence with them. The Com. Vote the Lords that ſubſcribed it, and thoſe with them traitors. The Committee of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the deſire of their houſe to the Common Councel, as to ſatisfaction about his Majeſties comming to <hi>London</hi> to treat, another meeting was appointed to reſolve upon ſome what.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>The</hi> 8.</label> Came news that Col: <hi>Roſſiter</hi> had ſo diſperſt the <hi>Pomfret</hi> party, that 450 were become his priſoners, all their plunder, and what elſe there's. This day came alſo the news of routing the Noble Army by the forces of Sir <hi>Miles Liveſy</hi> and of the Army, and that they were diſappointed of their ſport in <hi>Windſor</hi> Foreſt, many of them wounded, others taken, ſome ſlain, among whom was the Lord <hi>Francis Villers</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> refuſing quarter, they that eſcaped got over at <hi>Kingſton</hi> Bridge, ſome paſſing in boats, for the Commander in cheife cried Gent: ſhift for your ſelves, 10 <hi>lib</hi> for a boate: this routed party flies to <hi>Harrovv</hi> Hill, thence to <hi>Watford,</hi> but that proved to hot for them, &amp; ſo to <hi>Redburn,</hi> &amp; thence to <hi>Shefford,</hi> between <hi>Bedford</hi> &amp; <hi>Hitchin</hi> where they were, Saturday night, after whom, with 5 Troops went Major <hi>Gibbons,</hi> lately come from <hi>Kent.</hi> And to meet them with 6 Troops under Command of Col: <hi>Scroop</hi> from the Leagure before <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> who Sunday night was not far from them: the joynt forces that defeated them of <hi>Pomfret</hi> ſtand ready to receive them come they North: and to this royall party goe from <hi>London</hi> and other parts, very many horſe and foot with colours that diſtinguſhes them from the Parliaments forces, and openly enquire the way to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>The</hi> 10.</label> The Lords at a Conference did give reaſon for a Treaty with his Majeſty, he being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert
<pb facs="tcp:116550:6"/>berty before any acts be agreed upon. Firſt, its the deſire of the Kingdome or Parliament of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Secondly, the agreement will be the more Authentick. Thirdly, its probable having no Army in being, he wil condiſcend to that which at <hi>Vxbridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> he refuſed. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, its not the way of Treaties to confirme any before all is agreed, eſpecially thoſe of moſt concernment, and that which chiefly will be inſiſted upon, or to this effect, the Commons concurrence was deſired.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Dublin,</hi> June 28.</label> We are here happy (if the leaſt of happineſſe be to be in this unhappy Kingdom) in that we are ſo many mindes as parties, and all by that means at preſent in an incapacity to hurt cach other. <hi>Preſton</hi> and <hi>Owen Roe</hi> neer <hi>Athlone,</hi> ſtriving who may get the Caſtle from Mr. <hi>Audley</hi> the newter Governour, but he hath not, nor it's conceived will deliver it to either: <hi>Ovven</hi> and the Nuntio are in the Town on this ſide the water; no fighting hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them onely ſtraglers, yet they plunder each other daily, their miſeries great, roots are their chiefe food, bread being wanting: and yet it's to be feared they may at laſt agree, and out-live their wants, we being not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>capacity to increaſe them and fall upon us. The Scots have ſo much inveigled divers of our horſe, that many are gone to them (there's a fourth party) they give 20 ſh. advance, and 8d. <hi>per diem</hi> to a man, during their ſtay in the Kingdom, for it's pretended they muſt goe for <hi>Scotland:</hi> On the other ſide divers come to Col: <hi>Monk,</hi> from <hi>Munroe</hi> with their cows and cattell: Col: <hi>Monk</hi> is poſſeſt of <hi>Dandalke,</hi> Col: <hi>Moors</hi> Regiment, being not great, is brought to this City, and is to be reduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 2 Companies, My Lord <hi>Inchequins</hi> Forces in wants enough as well as we, and thus ſtands the State of the five parties at preſent, when any action will be is uncertain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Leagure before</hi> Colcheſter, July 8, 1648.</label> Yeſterday the enemy had planted a ſmall Drake on the Bels frame in St. <hi>Maries</hi> ſteeple, and from it made ſome ſhot, Col. <hi>Rainsborow</hi> waiting upon my Lord, to the battery made a ſhot in at the window, which we are credibly informed ſhot the Gunner through the belly. This we are certain, that they never made ſhot from that place ſince, and it is ſaid, he was their beſt Cannoneer. Upon ſome volleys of ſhot yeſterday towards the evening at the buriall of Lie vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naut Col. <hi>Shamb ook,</hi> the enemy made their Souldiers believe relief was come, and the wals and Steeples was full of people to ſee it come. Eighteen of our ſouldiers which were priſoners, and this day releaſed, complain, that from Wedneſday to Saturday, they had but three peny loaves of bread, and each man an ounce of fleſh, and a pale of water allowed. We heare the enemy hath drawn all their horſe and foot together, cauſeth all their fire locks to be brought into a Church, and all manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> horſes, with ſuch furniture as the Town can make to be ready, whereby, we conceive, they will attempt to eſcape with as many of their foot as they can mount their horſe being ſo ſtraited that they have nothing left for them but green corn. Neer 20 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted them this day, and came into us, they tell that proviſion is very ſcarce, and what there is they cannot eat but for meere hunger. We ſent them in a Liſt of the priſoners taken in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> by Major Gen. <hi>Lambe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Colcheſter <hi>Legu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</hi> July 11.</label> Our Line goes ſo faſt on, that we are in far better caſe to offend the enemy, and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond with <hi>Suffolk</hi> men, many of their ſouldiers come to us, the people of the Town in great want; all their bread is made of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and but half grownd; and that (not without a Ticket) their hay gone, the green Corn they get for their horſe, they fetch with hazard of the lives of their men: yeſterday having placed a guard to ſecure thoſe who came to get horſneat, the guard was bear by us, divers of them killed, ſome taken, great ſhooting with cannon from both ſides; they have ſpent very much powder: more yeſterday then in ten days before. Wee raiſed this night a new battery, to beat them our of St. <hi>Maries</hi> ſteeple, where they have planted a Demi culvering, which annoys us in our new Quarters. We have two whole Culverings play hard againſt the Lord <hi>Lucas</hi> houſe; the women would
<pb facs="tcp:116550:6"/>come by hundreds out of the Town, but that is not permitted. Captain <hi>Veſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y,</hi> upon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of his wiſe is pardoned, and hath a protection from violence, ſome of both ſides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laſt night neer each other, fell to parley and proved old acquaintance, it ſeems they were ſome of ours disbanded, in which act we have ſeen our errour, but no more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Nevvcaſtle,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uly 6.</label> You have had the deſeat of <hi>Langdales</hi> horſe by an expreſſe from our Governour, to adde a little, the priſoners of quality were moſt taken in their beds, being aſſured by Col: <hi>Grey,</hi> their Cheifrain, that there was no danger, they were neer 1200, ours 900. Col: <hi>Rich. Tempeſt</hi> eſcap'd from <hi>Morpeth,</hi> by feeling the hand of the ſentinell, 60 common Souldiers alſo eſcap'd in the darke, diverſe of the com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n Souldiers ſerve willingly in this Town: The Scots Army he on the borders not yet come in Gen: <hi>Langdale</hi> undertooke to cleere the Counties of <hi>Cumberland, Weſtmerland, Northumberland,</hi> and Biſhoprick, to make way for the Scots Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and ſo bring them into contribution to the Scots. <hi>Cumberland</hi> is much exhauſted. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Gen: <hi>Lambert</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emains before <hi>Carlile,</hi> and keeps thoſe up within: The Forces here are reſolved to goe towards their Major Gen: being now 33 Troops of horſe, Col: <hi>Hariſon</hi> being joyned, and to attend the motion of the Scots, or further the gaining the City: It's reſolved by the Engliſh Forces to fight, if there come but 20000 horſe and ſcor. On the other ſide, the Scots now upon the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ders muſt come in, for otherwiſe their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uldiers will ſpoyle their count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey, and grow diſcont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, having their expectations upon <hi>England,</hi> many common Souldiers who made it appear, they were forc'd, are ſet at liberty, divers that come in as common Souldiers, are found ſince to be Gentlemen of quality, as it's probable were ſome of thoſe that eſcaped, they were ſo full of gold, which they parted with at under value, though bought over, that common Troopers got 15, 16, 18, and 20 <hi>lib.</hi> a man, good cloaths, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, piſtols, ſwords, &amp;c. a ſubſidy will hardly recrute them as they were: 15 of the chiefe are ſent into <hi>Tinmouth, viz.</hi> Col: <hi>Grey</hi> Col: <hi>Ogle,</hi> Sir <hi>Iervis Lucas,</hi> 2 <hi>Collinvvoods,</hi> and others, the reſt ſerured in this Town, where they are as merry and frollick as if they had had the victory, and ſpend as if they had as good mines of money a we of coales. Some are of opinion the Scots will not come in, but be aſſured they will, and therefore haſten a reſerre for Major Gen: <hi>Lambert</hi> as faſt as you can, in regard the number of Officers are more then before mentioned, they are inſerted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A Liſt of priſoners taken <hi>Iuly</hi> 1. 1648.</label> Col: <hi>Edward Grey</hi> Commander in chief. Sir <hi>Francis Ratcliffe.</hi> Sir <hi>Iervis Lucas.</hi> Col: <hi>Iobn Tempeſt.</hi> Col: <hi>Iames Ogle.</hi> L. Col: <hi>Iohn Salkeild.</hi> L. Col: <hi>Ralph Millet:</hi> L. Col: <hi>Iohn Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> M. <hi>Roger Ratcliffe.</hi> M. <hi>Galeyn Ratcliffe.</hi> Col: <hi>Ratcliffe.</hi> L. Col. <hi>Anthony Trellop.</hi> Major <hi>Trollop.</hi> Cap <hi>George Rellaſis.</hi> Mr. <hi>George Collingvvood.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Collingvvood.</hi> Cap. <hi>Hugh Iames.</hi> Cap. <hi>Francis Carlton.</hi> Cap. <hi>Francis Brandling.</hi> Cap. <hi>Fetherſtonhaugh.</hi> Cap: <hi>Aſcue.</hi> Cap. <hi>Cholmley wright.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Salkeild</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>net. Mr. <hi>Will. Hodgſhon.</hi> Mr. <hi>Charles Selby.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Thirlvvell. Mr. Will. Lampton.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lanclot Selby</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Woodhouſe.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ralph Claxton.</hi> Licurenant <hi>Lance Procter.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cuthbert Kennet.</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter Forcer.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ambroſe Carlton.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Fitzvvilliams.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Hardy.</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Cope.</hi> M. <hi>Iohn Wright.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iames Shaſtoe.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ingram Stellinge.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Tempeſt.</hi> Cap. <hi>Smith.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Farneley.</hi> Mr. <hi>Per. Warden,</hi> Corner. Mr. <hi>Iohn Goodman.</hi> Enſigne <hi>Tho. Burrell.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lodovvick Burnell.</hi> Mr. Iohn <hi>Siſon.</hi> Mr. <hi>In. Watſon.</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Holmes.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hen. Brahant.</hi> Mr <hi>Ralph Bovves.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cartvvridge. Bilton. Shavv. Thampſan. Rigmadan.</hi> Serjeants. Beſides 309 common-Souldiers, and between 5 or 600 horſe, with their piſtols and ſwords.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Pembrook <hi>Leagure, July</hi> 3.</label> Friday morning laſt; about break of day, the enemy made a very ſtout ſally on the North ſide, upon Col: <hi>Reades</hi> Quarters with neer 300, there being of them onely 80 horſe, they were upon our men, through a ſally port, ere they were aware, but after ours got handſomly together, they ſo bang'd them, that there went into the Town 40 and upward wounded, 11
<pb facs="tcp:116550:7"/>killed under our works, 9 taken priſoners, their Commander in chiefe one Major <hi>Williams</hi> ſlain, we loſt one Lieutenant <hi>Potts,</hi> a Serjeant, 2 ſouldiers, and 2 or 3 more were wounded, they are well nigh ſtarv'd, run daily forth to us, we believe a few dayes will give us the Town, but our guns are not yet come up to us, which is a great inconvenience and much troubles us, had they come, we had done our work before this, and been ready for the North to receive the forward if they come out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and encourage the ſuffering party.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Seneeds, July 11. <hi>five in the morning.</hi>
                     </label> The party of horſe commanded by Col. <hi>Scroop,</hi> ſent from the Leagure before <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> to meet with the Noble Army, came to <hi>Hartford,</hi> Saturday, where they got knowledge of their enemies poſture and place of quarter, they got from <hi>Hartford</hi> ſome skilfull guides who brought them the neereſt and beſt way to <hi>Seneeds,</hi> Monday morning, before the Nobles could ſhift away, yet not before they were got into three bodies in the Towne. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Forlorn being entred, charged, routed them before the body came up, but when come up, there was ſpeedy work made with them, that in an inſtant they fled ſeverall ways; yet many fell, and of the chief, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> fled with about 60 horſes to <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> who muſt either diſperſe or fall into the hands of that party of <hi>Leiceſter, Lincolne,</hi> &amp;c. which lately defeated the <hi>Pomfret</hi> party; for our march was ſo long, and our horſe ſo tyred, that we could not purſue: we have priſoners the Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard,</hi> Col. <hi>Skeimiſher,</hi> Major <hi>Holland,</hi> Major <hi>Slepkin,</hi> Lievtenant Col. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and Col. <hi>Dolbeere</hi> mortally wounded, one Col. <hi>Legg</hi> in the ſame condition, 100 common men, and yet no ordinary men, Sir <hi>Kenelme Digbyes</hi> ſon ſaid to be ſlain, a Col. and divers other Officers ſlain, whoſe names we cannot yet learn, we had more then 100 gallant horſe, for gold and ſilver, good clothes and weapons, good and good ſtore.</p>
                  <p>It's beleeved the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and thoſe with him will deſiſt and ſeeke mercie. Lord <hi>Andover</hi> going to the Prince, is taken, and put into <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle.</p>
                  <p>We had two men ſlain, Col. <hi>Scroops,</hi> Captain Lievtenant wounded, and three more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>July</hi> 12. There came an expreſſe from the Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> which certifies the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that he had received a Letter and Declaration from Duke <hi>Hambleton,</hi> which tels him that the Parl. of <hi>England</hi> had not given ſatisfaction to the Parl. of <hi>Scotland</hi> in their deſires ſent unto them, for effecting whereof he was to come with an Army into the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in which enterprize, he expected no oppoſition from him. The Major Gen: returned him anſwer, that as to <hi>non</hi> ſatisfaction from the Parl. of <hi>England,</hi> he had not to ſay; but as to his comming in an hoſtile way into <hi>England,</hi> he had authority from Parl. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſift to his utmoſt any power not raiſed by them, and he <hi>[that]</hi> muſt expect if he came upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground. The Commons vote, they approve what Major Gen: <hi>Lambert</hi> had ſent, deſire the Lords concurrence, which the Lords doe, and both agree the Committee of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> houſe draw up againſt morning an anſwer to the Declaration of the Duke, to be preſented to the Houſe. A Petition of many thouſand houſholders of quality, in <hi>London,</hi> and parts about, was this day preſented, praying the Lords and Commons, that in a Treaty for peace or agreement, they will keepe up cloſe to their many Declarations and proteſtation formerly made, for which, both Houſes give them thanks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Walmer</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Kent</hi> yielded, they march out with ſwords.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>Printed for <hi>R. Leybourn.</hi> in <hi>Monk-well-ſtreet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <p>Imprimatur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>G. Mabbor.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <trailer>This is the true <hi>Moderate Intelligencer.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
